<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Way Back</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://the-way-back.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://the-way-back.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2018 10:04:05 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2018 10:04:05 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Slaughter Day + 1: Part 3, Butchering Pigs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Where we left off in my previous post on processing pigs, the pigs had been eviscerated and split and were hanging to cool overnight. This post will describe the process of butchering a pig: taking it from a side or half down to what we know of as retail cuts, i.e., pork chops, spare ribs, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, the first task is to break each side down into primal cuts. Primal cuts are the five main subdivisions in each side, which are further subdivided to yield retail cuts. These cuts are 1) the ham 2) the belly 3) the loin 4) the Boston butt, and 5) the picnic shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the following cuts and butchering procedures are somewhat difficult to describe in text. I’ve found it’s helpful to have a diagram and/or video to refer to, especially where the cut is determined by the location of a particular bone or anatomic feature. For a very good intro video, I’m posting this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7sVVqx8vvA0&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;  to Gregg Rentfrow’s excellent 45 minute clip on pork butchering. This is the video I learned from and the below text mostly follows his sequence of cuts with a few exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making pork cuts is a fairly arbitrary process, depending largely on what your meat preferences are. Those who like bone-in pork chops and loin steaks are in for some tricky work with the bone saw; whereas conversely, it’s not inconceivable to turn an entire pig into sausage, if that pig is well past ideal slaughter weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When butchering, we work outdoors on a stainless steel food service table set up near our slaughter area. Our pork sides are hanging nearby, and it is easiest to work with the meat outdoors in late fall or winter in conditions where it will also (hopefullly) stay cool until it is finally packaged or rubbed down with cure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first cuts I make are with the bone saw. I cut the feet off of both the front and hind legs. These cuts are made just above the knee joints. Pigs feet are not a delicacy we enjoy, so if we do save them, it is to later pick the meat off for sausage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the feet removed, I then turn to the ham. The ham is cut from the rest of the carcass after locating the aitch bone, which is part of the halved pelvic girdle. With the bone saw, I begin cutting two inches above the aitch bone (towards the loin) with the path of the saw running perpendicular to the shank, or extended leg, of the ham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To visualize this cut, imagine the shank pointing straight up in the air if you were to set the cut face of the ham flat on a table. Once the saw is through the bone, I cut through the meat and skin below it with a sharp butcher knife. As a general rule, always use a knife to cut flesh and a saw (or hatchet or cleaver) to sever bone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the ham completely separated from the rest of the halved carcass, it can be cured or frozen, depending on preference. We make country ham or prosciutto with these cuts; both processes require curing in salt or cure mix and at least a year before the meat will be ready to eat, though I can definitely say the wait is worth it. I will cover the specifics of preparing country ham and prosciutto in the next post in this series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I separate the shoulder and Boston butt from the carcass. To do this, saw straight across the carcass from a point between the second and third rib. You will be cutting through bone almost the entire way: the backbone as well as the shoulder bone. When you get down to the skin and the fat, use a knife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these two cuts separated from the carcass, they can be further broken down. First though, the backbone and first two ribs should be removed by following the contours of the bones with a knife and separating them from the rest of the cut. With that out of the way, sever the shoulder from the Boston butt by finding the shoulder blade and cutting with a knife about an inch below it (toward the shoulder). When you hit bone, cut through it with a saw and then continue with a knife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We generally use the shoulder for sausage though it can be cured and smoked like ham. The Boston butt can be cut down further into pork steaks or used for sausage, though we usually try to save most of this cut for slow-cooked pulled pork barbecue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the front and back ends of the side removed, the loin and belly remain. We cut the belly out in one or two large sections. The belly is the easily to identify boneless fatty section below the ribs. We cut this off following the bottom ribline with a sharp butcher knife or boning knife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we usually have a group of friends present to help us with butchering, we try to remove the ham and bacon first, before making any other retail cuts. These need to be vigorously rubbed with cure and, in the case of bacon, sealed in plastic for the duration of the cure time. To expedite the work of butchering, it’s a good idea to have one or several friends or volunteers working on curing and packing bacon and ham while the other less labor intensive (processing wise, anyway) cuts are still underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the bacon/belly has been removed, we saw through the ribs, starting about two inches from the backbone on the front side of the carcass (where the Boston butt and picnic have been removed). Sawing straight across lengthwise will separate the spare ribs from the rest of the loin. The spare ribs can now be further broken down into meal-sized portions and packaged, removing any remaining cartilage or fatty tissuse along the sternum end of the ribs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With only the loin section left, we cut the layer of back fat away from the rest of the meat cuts, using a sharp but flexible boning knife. The goal is to avoid cutting into the rest of the loin meat while removing the dense layer of fat that is attacheed to the hide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we cut out the sirloin, identified by the curvy bulge at one end of the loin section. The cut is made where the bulge tapers back into the rest of the loin section, starting between two vertebrae of the backbone and working downward parallel with the ribs. The sirloin is then further broken down into boneless sirloin chops by cutting away the bony section and slicing chops from the large remaining steak. We cut these about an inch thick. Scraps are saved for sausage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the rest of the loin, we separate the ribs using the same technique as the spare ribs: by running a sharp boning knife along the border between the ribs and the loin meat. With this cut made, we flip the loin over and make the same cut from the outside, but this time following the edge of the backbone. The ribs are connected to the backbone at about a 90-degree angle. With a bone saw and a knife, we then subdivide the ribs into meal or portion-sized cuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After removing the remaining blade bone and striated fatty section from the tubular loin section, the loin is broken down into pork chops or sausage. We enjoy sausage more than chops, and so tend to make only a few cuts for chops and/or larger loin roasts, and designate a greater proportion of the loin meat for sausage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any other scraps and remainders from earllier on in the process also make it into the sausage pile, where they will later be cut into about one-inch cubes and sorted according to whether they are primarily fat or lean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I have attempted to outline our general process of making primal and retail cuts of pork, though I realize it is by no means a thorough or exhaustively technical description.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As previously noted, those who are intersted in learning pork butchery would do well to also consult a video or book with many photos and diagrams, before attempting to break down a side of pork. Even better, enlist the help of an experienced butcher for your first pig slaughter, as we did during our first slaughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next installment of this series, I will cover the general process of curing and smoking ham and bacon and making sausage, as well as covering a few details on packaging and storing pork. At the end of that post, I will also provide a list of resources I have found helpful that pertain to all stages of slaughtering, butchering and processing pork.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2018 02:09:59 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2018/02/20/pig-slaughter-3.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2018/02/20/pig-slaughter-3.html</guid>
        
        <category>pigs</category>
        
        <category>slaughtering</category>
        
        <category>butchering</category>
        
        <category>ethical-meat</category>
        
        <category>eviscerating</category>
        
        <category>splitting</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Slaughter Day: Part 2, Eviscerating and Splitting Pigs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the my previous post, the first in this series, I sought to provide a detailed description of the process for humanely slaughtering, scalding, and scraping a hog. In the current post, I will endeavor to describe the next steps involved in processing pigs, covering evisceration and splitting the carcass, after which point the hog can be further broken down into primal cuts. I will discuss butchering (i.e., working from primal cuts to “retail” cuts), sausage-making, curing, smoking, and otherwise processing the pork in further posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From where we left off at the end of the first post, our pig was hanging away from the scalding vat on the second engine hoist, where it had been weighed on a hanging spring scale. Its head should now be facing down and almost touching the ground. We typically put an old shipping pallet between the ground and the hanging carcass to keep it off of what has usually become at this point a muddych, due to water dripping from the vat and the carcass, as well as heavy foot traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We remove the head from the body before beginning the evisceration. To do this, we cut around the perimeter of the neck where it meets the shoulder with a long, sharp knife. This usually takes a few tries before all of the flesh is severed. Next, take the head in both hands, holding around the ears, and snap the head briskly. This should crack the neck and separate the head from the carcass. It may take a few tries and a little clean-up work with the knife to completely sever the head. We set it aside after separating it from the carcass and put it in a cooler on ice. Later we will harvest the jowl bacon and cook down the head to make head cheese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, the pig can be lowered to a comfortable working height where we can begin the process of evisceration by cutting a wide swath of flesh just beneath the pig’s tail and encircling the anus by a comfortable working margin. The goal here is to cut away the end of the intestinal tract from the surrounding flesh so that it may be tied off and then removed in one piece when the abdominal cavity has been cut open. It is very important to avoid severing the intestines while making this cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequences of nicking or cutting the intestine range from a stinky and unpleasant job of continuing the disembowelment to the potentially serious fecal contamination of the meat. If the intestine is cut, the carcass can be thoroughly hosed out after splitting (a good practice, and one that we follow, in any case). When the rectum has been cut away from the surrounding flesh on all sides, it is important to securely tie it closed with a piece of twine. With this done, it’s time to begin cutting through the abdominal cavity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lightly score the skin on the underside of the carcass starting from the point where the intestine has been cut out and tied off downward through the centerline of the abdomen and through to the sternum (breastbone). Using the score mark as a guide, cut through the flesh between the anus and the pelvic girdle. The pelvic girdle is the first bony mass you will encounter working towards the head; it should be carefully split with a hatchet, meat cleaver or bone saw. We prefer to use the bone saw, working the saw as close to the lines of the knife cut as possible (not pushing the saw into the abdominal cavity, if possible).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the hog is a male, the urethra will appear beneath the skin soon after cutting through the pelvic girdle. Tie this off with a piece of twine or string as you did with the end of the intestinal tract and cut off the penis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the pelvic girdle split, we cut through the center of the belly with a knife. To do this without risking a cut to the intestines or organs, some technique is required: Hold a knife blade with the tip facing down (in the direction of travel towards the pig’s neck with the blade just inside the skin of the abdominal cavity). With the other hand inside the abdominal cavity between the knife and the internal organs, cup or shield the tip and blade of the knife so that neither will accidentally cut into anything besides the layer of skin, the only thing between you and the knife blade at this point. The action of pushing the knife down the carcass while angled slightly outward facing toward you is a little like unzipping a jacket where the knife is the zipper. If you have a knife with a guthook and are familiar with its use in field dressing an animal in a hunting context, this is the same idea, and a guthook could be used here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the abdominal cavity has been cut open down to the breastbone, split the breastbone with a hatchet, cleaver, or bone saw. We prefer the bone saw, though it can be a challenge to make this cut with the saw with the pig in a hanging position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At any point in this process, the pig’s innards may begin to spill out. We typically place a large plastic tub or “gut bucket” on the pallet near the carcass. This serves as a receptacle in which to place the intestines and organs as the abdominal cavity is opened up. To remove them completely, reach into the carcass and tear away the connective tissue that holds the intestines and organs to the inside of the pelvis, ribs, and chest, beginning with the tied-off end of the intestines and working downward to the stomach, liver, gall bladder, spleen, and kidneys. Avoid puncturing the liver and gall bladder when removing them. Next, remove the heart, lungs, and esophagus. When you have finished removing viscera, the abdominal cavity of the pig will appear smooth and relatively clean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The organs of the pig can and should be saved for later use. They can be washed off and iced down to be processed after the pig is split. The liver can be eaten cooked, in pate, or ground into an emulsion to make liverwurst. The kidneys can be served fried in butter and seasoned with salt and pepper (as memorably eaten for breakfast by Leopold Bloom in Joyce’s &lt;em&gt;Ullyses&lt;/em&gt;) or baked along with beef steak in the traditional British dish of steak and kidney pie. Intestines can be cleaned out and later used for sausage casings. Some also enjoy eating the heart, though the heart and lungs, when we have saved them in the past, have usually ended up as dog food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost every part of the pig, including the blood, can be eaten cooked or prepared as sausage filling. Admittedly, during most pig slaughters, we are usually too time-crunched and lacking in cold storage space to make use of every organ, though we do aspire to use as much of the pig as possible. In practice though, the intestines and some of the organs tend to end up buried underground due to limited fridge and freezer space and the general rush to process three (or more) pigs in an always too narrow window of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before splitting the carcass, we prefer to remove the tenderloins or  “fish,” as they are otherwise known. These two cylindrical, tapering cuts of pork are prized by many above all others, but they can be easily damaged by a bone saw during the process of sawing the carcass in half. They are located within the abdominal cavity towards the middle-back of the pig. These can be removed with a knife or torn away from the carcass. We usually divide these up amongst our team of volunteers as a thank-you gift for their help with the slaughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Splitting the carcass from bottom to top through the spine is one of the most labor-intensive parts of the slaughter and entails the use of a manual bone saw or an electric power saw of some variety. In past years, we have attempted to use an electric reciprocating saw (or sawzall) to split the carcass, though this proved difficult to control and somewhat damaging to the meat cuts. In general, I prefer the upper-body workout of using a manually operated bone saw, though an electric jigsaw did come into play cutting through one particularly stubborn section of bone during this year’s slaughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To split the carcass, we first score the hide on the back of the hog. This creates a visual reference point for helpers to follow the track of the saw and thus warn the cutter if the saw is straying from the center. We begin by sawing through the middle of the spine where it terminates near the tail. The carcass, since it is hanging, will tend to pull and bind the blade of the saw in one direction or the other, and the cut we made through which we eviscerated (and through which the saw must travel) will close up, if not forcefully held open. For this reason, I like to have a helper on each side holding open the walls of the abdominal cavity, either with boning hooks or bare hands. This gives me room to work and adequate light to judge whether or not the saw is on the right track through the center of the spine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intensity of labor involved in cutting through the spine and back varies, as it is thicker and bonier in certain spots, though it generally takes at least a few minutes and a few pauses to realign the saw blade as it veers off center. The precision with which the pig is split is a point of pride for me, though really it is a relatively minor detail that slightly impacts the overall quality of bone-in pork chops and ribs if done poorly; ultimately, however, these are not particularly important cuts for us. While we do like our barbecued ribs, it is country ham, bacon, and sausage that hold the main attraction for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the length of the backbone sawn in half from top to bottom, both sides of pork will separate. As the carcass comes apart, each helper should keep hold of their side, as these will tend to rock back and forth, hanging as they are from the rear leg on a see-sawing gambrel. Depending on the weight of the pig at slaughter, each side may still be quite heavy, well over 100 pounds, usually. It’s definitely a good idea to have at least two people on hand to handle or move each side of pork. Halving or splitting the pork carcass is typically the culmination of the day’s process for each particular pig until the meat has had time to cool overnight from body temperature to ambient temperature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warm meat is much harder to cut and work with than cold or almost frozen meat. Furthermore, cuts such as bacon and hams won’t absorb curing agents until they have cooled significantly. Before nightfall we hang each side close to our house and securely out of reach of predators. The next morning, after the outside temperature has dropped significantly, the pork will be much easier to work with, when we will break it down into primal cuts and then further into so-called “retail” cuts, the ones most cooks are familiar with, a topic to be covered in the next post in this series.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2018 02:09:59 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2018/01/28/pig-slaughter-2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2018/01/28/pig-slaughter-2.html</guid>
        
        <category>pigs</category>
        
        <category>slaughtering</category>
        
        <category>butchering</category>
        
        <category>ethical-meat</category>
        
        <category>eviscerating</category>
        
        <category>splitting</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Slaughter Day: Part 1, Slaughtering and Scalding Pigs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A month ago, Tasha and I and several friends spent a long weekend immersed in what has come to be for us an annual event - slaughering our pigs. It’s never a day we look forward to especially, but when the days grow short and the overnight temperatures dip into the 30s, our thoughts turn to planning the pig slaughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year as in past years, our main concern has been to dispatch each pig as painlessly and humanely as possible. The Wendell Berry poem, “For the Hog Killing,” has become for us a sort of invocation at slaughter time, as well as a standard to uphold: “let them die while the sound of the shot is in the air, let them die as they fall.” In other words, as one commentator on the poem has put it, let the slaughter take place “with a minimum of violence.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tasha and I respect the lives of all the animals we care for, maybe even more so the ones we know we will eventually have to slaughter. LIke all the pigs we’ve raised, we cared for these from the time we brought them onto our farm as piglets until, over the course of the better part of a year, they’d grown to almost 400 pounds. Unlike past years, these piglets were obtained from our friends and neighbors Donnie and Anita Collins, whose breeding pair of Berkshires had produced these three males.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the time we moved them onto our farm in early spring, the pigs had as carefree a life as we were able to manage for them, never wanting for food, water or shelter, and having almost an acre of paddock to root and forage on. When the heat set in over the summer, we provided them with a wallow, watching them roll happily in the mud or doze in the shade of a thicket of bushes and trees. They had a good life here indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Joel Salatin has famously said, “So what if the pig has one bad day?” But we have endeavored to eliminate even that one bad day, slaughtering here on our farm instead of having it done at a commercial abbatoir. Ideally, the pig is shot in the forehead with a .22 rifle while feeding and then loses consciousness from the shot. While unconcious, his jugular vein or carotid artery is immediately severed with a stroke of the knife, and within seconds or a minute or two at most, succumbs from loss of blood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bleeding a pig is a necessary part of processing pork and recovering edible meat. With this in mind, it is also crucial to the process on practical as well as ethical grounds that the pig not be stressed or frightened before the slaughter, as the stress hormones that are rapidly dispersed into the pig’s bloodstream can sour the meat. This is just one more reason to carry out the slaughter with the utmost care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year our friend Tom, an avid hunter, offered to be our shooter. He expertly took down each pig with a carefully placed shot to the forehead, straight between the eyes and about an inch or so up. For full effect, the shot must be placed perpendicular to the pig’s skull. This is trickier than it would seem, even at point-blank range, because the pigs are constantly moving around and jockeying for position to get closest to the food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the first pig–our largest–went over at the shot, I hopped the wires of the electric fence and stuck it in the neck with a very sharp boning knife. I swept the knife blade up and back until blood gushed forth in a thick stream, alerting me that I’d cut the right the vein. This pig was so large that I had some difficulty getting my arm around its neck to the spot where i needed to plant the knife, though I did quickly find it and make the cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the next two pigs, I opted to make the stick almost at the breast and closer to the heart, a technique I’d seen done before, but one with which I had less practice. The cut involves sticking the knife in just above the pig’s breastplate and sweeping the knifeblade under to sever the carotid artery just above the heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/HMPQP9J.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;Tools of the Trade: Butcher Knife, Boning Knife and Straight Razor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With either of the two techniques, whether severing the jugular vein or carotid artery at the neck, or the carotid artery closer to the heart, a quick and humane death and a good bleed are ensured, if done properly. Having now gained more experience with the second technique, I feel it is the better way to go, especially with larger animals with a lot of fat around the jowl and neck, which makes locating the right spot in the neck a little more difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to avoid the repetitious description of the identical process involved in scalding and butchering each slaughtered pig, I’ll try rather to encapsulate and summarize the salient details and describe the process more abstractly from here on. I will also note that from shooting and sticking to splitting the carcass takes us on average about two hours for each pig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When each pig had finished bleeding out and we were certain that it was no longer alive, we attached ropes to its feet and dragged it the twenty-odd feet to our 4” x 6” crossbeam where we had hung a couple of engine hoists suspended over a scalding vat a little more than half full of 150-degree water. It’s important to leave room in the tank for the water the carcass will displace. No one likes to be burned by overflowing water as the pig is lowered into the tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tank, incidentally, started life as a heating oil tank before it was used as a stock tank on a local farm. It was brought to us by our friend Ted the first year we slaughtered pigs because we had trouble finding a large enough tank we could safely heat. With a few welded modifications and a spigot to easily drain water from the bottom, we had a custom-built tank that would be big enough for our pigs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/HX9Obxo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;Scalding Station with Engine Hoists&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing the 60 gallons of water necessary to scald a pig up to 150 degrees and holding it there for the duration of the slaughter can be a challenge; it is sometimes the most time consuming part of preparing for a slaughter. Anticipating this, I now start the two propane burners that heat our scalding tank first thing in the morning–that is, around 5:00 AM if we are planning to start slaughtering at 9:00 AM. If the previous night’s lows dip into the 20s, there is frequently a layer of ice on the surface of the tank and the water will take several hours to reach temperature. One way we conserve heat is by covering the top of the tank with foam insulation board. If it is very windy we also try to enclose the underside of the tank where the burners are situated with cinder block, foam board or other insulative materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scalding and scraping is not a strictly necessary part of the process of butchering a pig. Like most other large animals, pigs can be skinned, and depending on your meat preferences and situation, this may be a better option for some. Since we prize our bacon cuts and hams above all else–the latter of which we turn into prosciutto or aged country ham–the skin is an important and necessary part for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the pig carcass transported as close to the scalding tank as possible, I use a very sharp boning knife to make cuts in each of the front and rear legs, between the bone and the strong, tight tendons just below the knee joints. This can be tricky work with a sharp knife, so slowly and carefully is the way to go here. When each set of cuts has been made, I insert a steel gambrel through both the front and the back legs. A gambrel (or singletree) is a sturdy hanger with curved, pointed tines on each end that fit through the slits in the legs. In the center of the gambrel is an eye for attaching a hook or connector at the end of a rope or chain with which to raise the carcass and lower it into the scalding tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/3iBZbQz.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;Tools of the Trade: Spring Scale, Gambrel, Boning Hook, Bell Scraper, Bone Saw&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the months before we first slaughtered pigs in 2015, I built a crossbeam from several lengths of pressure-treated 4” x 6” beams (see first photo). Two uprights set in concrete and braced diagonally at the base where they contact the ground suspend a horizontal beam about 10 feet in the air. The height is necessary to clear the top of the tank with the length of the vertically suspended pig. With the hope of scalding two pigs at a time (impractical as I now know), I drilled through the top of the crossbeam in two places and attached a heavy-duty eyebolt through each hole. From each eyebolt, we hang an engine hoist, which is simply a racheting, locking, geared pulley that provides a significant mechanical advantage for lifting a heavy object overhead. Pulling a chain loop attached to the gears either raises or lowers the attached object… very slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the front gambrel hooked to a chain attached to the engine hoist, one person pulls on the chain loop and begins ratcheting the carcass up and forward into the scalding tank, while at least two others hold onto the rear gambrel running through the back legs and steer the back half of the carcass up and over the rim of the scalding tank, carefully placing it into the hot water. Since the mass of the pig carcass will quickly absorb heat and lower the water temperature, it’s not a bad idea to heat the water hotter (155 or even 160 degrees) than the target temperature of 150 degrees, keeping in mind that contacting the flesh of the pig with the possibly overheated metal of the scalding tank may set the hair follicle, making it impossible to remove with a scraper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, we typically run at least three lengths of chain across the width of the scalding tank. With these in place, between the bottom of the tank and the mass of the carcass, people on either side can pull the chains, thus rotating the carcass and keeping it from settling on the bottom of the tank. While several volunteers are employed agitating these chains, another dumps buckets of hot water across the exposed parts of the carcass such as the legs, which never fully submerge in the tank. Every minute or so, it’s a good idea to check the status of the hair by yanking on a tuft of it. When hair pulls easily from several places, usually after about five minutes of submersion in hot water, the carcass should be raised as quickly as possible from the water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, the pig carcass is now hanging vertically over the tank and completely out of the water. Working as quickly as possible, four people, each one armed with a bell scraper (basically a bell-shaped hemisphere of metal attached to a handle), begin working the flesh. Ideally, the movement of the rough edge of the scraper over the hair follicle removes the heat-loosened hairs relatively easily. In practice, there are usually some parts that require the hair be shaved off with a knife blade or straight razor. If there are large areas of the pig where the hair doesn’t scrape off easily, then it’s usually necessary to return the carcass for another dip in the scalding vat, again making sure not to set the hair follicles by overheating the tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When each pig has been satisfactorily scalded and scraped, the second hoist comes into play as a means of lowering out, or transferring in tandem with the first hoist, the pig carcass onto a hanging spring scale attached to the second hoist, where it is weighed and processed further. Weighing is not strictly necessary either, but we like to collect as much data as possible to assess our feed-to-meat ratio, figure out our cost per pound, and so forth, and hanging weight is a key metric in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the pig now hanging on the second engine hoist and safely away from the scalding vat, we note the weight and lower it to a comforatble working height and begin the process of evisceration, which I will describe in detail in the second part of this series of posts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2018 02:09:59 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2018/01/16/pig-slaughter-1.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2018/01/16/pig-slaughter-1.html</guid>
        
        <category>pigs</category>
        
        <category>slaughtering</category>
        
        <category>butchering</category>
        
        <category>ethical-meat</category>
        
        <category>wendell-berry</category>
        
        <category>joel-salatin</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>At Rest, At Last</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year, everyone, and may 2018 be your best year yet! The second day of the new year finds Tasha and me taking it easy after what seems like a non-stop three weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around the middle of December, we began preparing for our pig slaughter and all that entails - getting together suppies, unpacking tools and equipment, checking our friends’ availability to help with the slaughter, processing, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m planning on posting a series on the pig slaughter in its entirety later, but suffice it to say we had a couple good days of weather, the help of a few amazing friends, and the better part of a week’s worth of solid work processing well over a thousand pounds of pork (live weight).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following weekend was Christmas, which kept us busy as usual for the next few days with family events and visits. It was a wonderful holiday and a great time to be together with family, several of whom traveled to North Carolina to spend the holiday at my parents’ house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between Christmas and New Year’s, we hosted two very gracious cousins from South Carolina, who were interested in touring our farm and discussing sustainable agriculture with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, we spent most of a day helping some good friends in Virginia with their final chicken slaughter of the year, as the cold wave that has been menacing the eastern third of the US since shortly after Christmas intensified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent much of the afternoon on New Year’s Eve preparing to host a few friends for a small New Year’s party, which went off very well. Tasha and I were thrilled to celebrate the New Year with a great group of friends, some of whom we haven’t seen in many months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyle and Nicole, who are also neighbors and who run nearby York Farm, announced the upcoming release of the film,&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ragtagtribe.com/beulahland/&quot;&gt;“Somewhere in Beulah Land,” &lt;/a&gt; by filmmaker Andrew Brown that will document a year of life on their farm. Tasha and I are thrilled for them and can’t wait to catch the premiere in Winston-Salem next month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After making it to dawn and then sleeping for a few hours, we spent much of New Year’s Day with our good friends Matthew and Jenna, who are likely moving back to the west coast in a few weeks. We’ll really miss them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we rounded out the day with dinner at my folks’ house: black-eyed peas and collard greens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With what feels like almost three weeks of non-stop excitement and activity coming to an end, it feels good to spend some time catching up on sleep, reading, and just generally enjoying a few days of rest before diving into a long list of projects for the new year. It’s too cold to do much outside now anyway!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 02:09:59 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2018/01/02/at-rest-at-last.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2018/01/02/at-rest-at-last.html</guid>
        
        <category>daily</category>
        
        <category>updates</category>
        
        <category>documentary</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Geminids</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Tasha and I watched the Geminids meteor shower last night. Since it was also a very cold night here in North Carolina, we combined our skywatching with dips in the hot tub, which we use to heat our greenhouse on nights when it gets down into the 20s or below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We typically soak in the hot tub for as long as we can stand and then cool off on the Adirondack chairs I built for this purpose a couple years ago, which sit just outside the greenhouse on the rim of the upper pond. After the Russian fashion, we alternate between extremes of hot and cold. Usually, this is just the thing to guarantee a wonderful night’s sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From where the chairs are, our property forms a sort of bowl, with the whole sky falling away in every direction. While it’s certainly no dark-sky area, the closest big cities are many miles away and even on a mediocre night, the Milky Way is usually faintly visible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I was a kid, I’ve been fascinated with the night sky, astronomy, cosmology, and celstial events. It’s only recently though, mostly in the years since we’ve moved onto the farm, that I’ve thought much about what it means to be human in relation to the night and the heavens above. I’ve written about this elsewhere (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.humansandnature.org/endarkenment&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;  and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.garrisoninstitute.org/blog/seen-unseen/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), and It’s a subject that I find myself returning to frequently, as our future here on our terrestrial home seems less and less certain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night we did see a few spectacular meteors, though by no means the 120 per hour forecast to occur at the peak (2:00 AM). We were watching between 8:00 and 9:00 PM, but the meteors we saw - at least 10 of them - were remarkable in their brightness and intensity, leaving long, luminescent trails as they streaked across the dome of night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between soaking in 110-degree water and cooling off in the brisk, near-freezing night air while watching the light show in the skies above, something in me was satisfied, and I slept better than I have in months.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2017 02:09:59 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/12/14/Geminids.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/12/14/Geminids.html</guid>
        
        <category>updates</category>
        
        <category>daily</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
        <category>essays</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Enough Time</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Shortly after I posted the most recent update on this blog, I decided to quit my job, in April 2017. This decision had been a long time coming, and seven months later, I find I still have no regrets about making it. While spending less and living on more that comes directly from our farm has taken some getting used to, I feel like I’ve mostly adjusted. I’m truly comfortable with the idea of having more time while earning less money. Oddly enough though, after freeing up 40 plus hours a week from my mostly work-from-home job, I soon found that I had seemingly less time than I did before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, I had vowed to take a few months off before diving into any major projects, spending as much of the late spring and early summer months as I could in the outdoors - hiking, climbing, running, etc. I spent most of May working around the farm trying to knock off a “short” list of relatively minor projects, like fixing the leak in the roof, doing a major cleanup around the farm before the arrival of out-of-town visitors, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the weather began to turn really nice, I did manage to spend a lot of time running. One week, I did 48 miles on the Blue Ridge Parkway. But soon after that, my achilles tendon began really bothering me, so I had to give up the running for a while. When it hadn’t recovered after about a month, I decided to spend one day a week doing some serious mileage hiking. For much of July and August, that’s what I did every Monday when the weather would cooperate. It was definitely easier on my body than the running, but the achilles tendon is still bothering me, in spite of several attempts at rehabilitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the summer, I found myself spending many of my Wednesdays helping a friend cut vegetables and prepare and jar ferments in her kitchen. Most Thursdays, I spent much of the day in my own kitchen, preparing baked goods for Tasha to sell at the Friday farmers market. I also set out on some more ambitious long term projects. One of these was building out the existing space of the bouldering wall I completed in the summer of 2016 to incorporate a sort of tiny house – a mixed-use space of about 128 square feet that is now completely enclosed and will eventually have its own power supply (when I get around to installing our spare 400-Watt PV system).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so along with doing some of the routine growing season maintenance and a few smaller writing projects, I found my time mostly accounted for as summer turned to fall. With the holidays fast approaching, I’m not quite sure where fall went either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the days grow shorter and shorter and the cold settles in, I’ve been doing a lot of reading and finally feeling that I’m ready to commit to some of the more ambitious writing projects that have been kicking around in my head for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Tasha and I first embarked on this adventure almost four years ago now, I had in my mind what I’m sure is a much-idealized vision of living like Wendell Berry as a poet/writer/farmer; of retreating to the woods like Henry David Thoreau or Joseph Campbell, to read, write, and think about it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as the year draws to a close and I begin to find a balance between contemplative pursuits and all of the other responsibilities, distractions, and detours I’ve found myself engaged with since April, I’m once again commiting to regularly maintaining this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More and more, I’ve come to see the importance of having a daily writing practice, and I hope to incorporate this blog as part of that. Moving forward, I’m not sure what form my posts will take. I’m less interested now in describing the projects we are working on here or in providing the typical prosaic updates about how we’ve spent our time since the last blog post. We’ll see what form they take, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s good to feel like I finally have enough time.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 02:09:59 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/12/12/enough-time.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/12/12/enough-time.html</guid>
        
        <category>updates</category>
        
        <category>daily</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
        <category>essays</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Three Years In: A Self-Assessment and the Work to Come</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, in the midst of a torrential downpour - Matt in the moving truck, me in my Honda Fit, and my dad in his car - we made our way from the suburbs of Washington, D.C. to our new home in rural North Carolina. The traffic around D.C. and Northern Virginia was horrendous, with accidents littering the roadways every few miles. Despite the total lack of visibility and flooded pockets of pavement, drivers were cutting each other off to get a few feet ahead, driving too fast when the traffic picked up, and slamming on their brakes repeatedly as if they were intentionally hoping to cause an accident too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As sad as I was about leaving our friends and family, that drive to our new life had felt like an affirmation of all the reasons why change was necessary. When we finally made it to Lowgap, I remember having a great sense of relief. It wasn’t just because we survived the drive, but that we had actually done “it.” We said goodbye to a way of living that felt destructive and silly but somehow stable, and had taken our first step towards something we hoped would be meaningful and regenerative, but that was also far more speculative than the beaten path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the days that followed, that sense of relief gave way to a question that we are effectively still trying to answer three years later. We had all sorts of plans about what our life here would look like. We’d studied a bunch of books, visited farms, talked to farmers, watched videos, made notes, and planned projects. As we started developing our food systems and installing infrastructure, it became clear that we had a made a pretty good road map for how to transform our landscape, but we hadn’t thought much about what it would take to be kind of people to best inhabit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite our progress, we have not yet answered the question “How do we become self-sufficient people?”
I’ve spent most of my life thinking that solutions came from stores, answers were out there, and professionals are necessary because I am only qualified to handle certain things on my own. One of the side-effects of a consumer culture is that our knowledge and skills have been narrowed down to what we get paid for and are considered qualified to do. We’ve become our jobs and our degrees, rather than a citizenry of well-rounded people with a high level of autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, our initial challenge has been to overcome those market dependencies by gaining skills through doing and developing effective replacement systems. To date, we’ve spent much of our time here experimenting, reading, trying, failing, improving, and eventually succeeding in the following areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing our own food in a greenhouse, in an annual garden, in food forests, on hugelkulturs, using aquaculture, with the use of livestock, mushroom cultivation, foraging, etc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building structures like animal shelters, a smokehouse, a pizza oven, and a greenhouse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Installing fences to keep some animals in and others out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Water management – e.g., pond building, swales, hugelkulturs, diversion channels, rain depressions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ecological restoration and wildlife and pollinator habitat creation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building community&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Food preparation – cheese, vinegar, wine, fermented foods, bread, pizza, etc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing a mix of homestead products for sale to local markets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Miscellaneous skills like welding for Matt and soap-making for Tasha&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Writing about our experiences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, the more skilled we become, the more we understand that it isn’t just our loss of skills that inures us to the system - it’s the very way we frame our questions and answers. We think in terms of goods and services. We are habituated to transactional living. And our choices are colored by addiction to products and services that we can’t, and shouldn’t try to, reproduce at the homestead level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is evident that even our notions of what constitutes problems, and how we go about solving them, stems from consumer culture. For example, a while back, our dishwasher broke. My first thought was, we’ll have to buy a new one. But then I reminded myself I was now a competent homesteader and should try to fix it. I tried and failed. Matt and I contemplated whether we really needed a dishwasher. We can’t run it on solar panels. We know it’s not sustainable. But the alternative of hand-washing when we have limited counter space, painfully shallow sinks, and use so many dishes for all food preparation activities seemed unmanageable with all our other time commitments. We decided a new dishwasher was a luxury, but one that we would indulge in for now and try to wean ourselves from down the road. We effectively did a cost benefit analysis and chose perceived convenience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I say “perceived” because when framed in the context of becoming self-sufficient people, it was a totally wrong answer. We’re now newly invested in an expensive technology that requires the use of electricity that we cannot generate ourselves. Regardless of the propaganda by dishwasher advocates, we know it is far more energy efficient to do dishes by filling a small tub of soapy water for washing and scrubbing and just rinsing quickly under running water. And the fact that we use so many dishes is an indication that we still have some simplification to do to become self-sufficient. A new dishwasher isn’t a convenience on the road to self-sufficiency, it’s a lengthy and unnecessary detour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dishwasher is an expensive item and obviously not sustainable, so it’s an easy example to point to. The real challenges though are not in the big decisions; we know the right answers on those even if we choose otherwise. The small and daily decisions have a larger cumulative effect than a one-time purchase of a dishwasher. And these, are in fact the habits we find most difficult to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started this adventure with the notion that we would use the easy availability of consumer products to fast-track our way to self-sufficiency. And that philosophy has served us well to a point. But now we need to make the next step in our transition and cut our ties to consumer culture, even if it feels like a hardship until we adjust. In truth, we don’t know exactly what this looks like because we have not seen it in our lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt and I both have early memories of being marketed to as children watching Saturday morning cartoons or re-runs of The Dukes of Hazard. If you doubt the pervasiveness of the messages, then think back to your favorite toy. Was it home-made or store bought? How long was it your favorite? How many other toys did you have? If are in the forty-something age bracket (like us), did you have a big wheel or a cabbage patch doll, or know someone who did? There’s a high probability that many of you in our age range have similar memories and experiences. And that’s not just a coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though Matt and I both rebelled in our youth becoming “alternative,” we each have stories of owning Creepers and Doc Martens, and other similar brand-named alternative attire. That too is not an accident. Fashion took over punk rock before we knew it existed. Nearly anything that starts as an authentic movement eventually gets co-opted by the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now with the internet, marketing has become even more pervasive and directed. As I click through websites on homesteading, animal husbandry, building a gray water system, composting toilet, DIY anything… related ads start to pop-up. Recently I was reading a post on “What Homesteading Really Costs…” I could only read a short section without scrolling because most of the screen was covered by advertisements for chicken coops and cattle panels (since I’d recently been searching those). In the post, the author wrote about having to pay for fences, roads, rebuilding structures, how she started blogging to make some money, but then she became an essential oils saleswoman and her husband was able to quit his job and build their dream home. And you can become a sales rep too, and support her dream of homesteading, while also supporting yours…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that the idea of the self-sufficient life has now also been usurped by advertising and an alternative product list. But Matt and I don’t want a simulacrum of a self-sufficient life. We genuinely want to opt out, not just to buy into an alternate version. And we know the only real way to do that is to learn to live without spending money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we first started this journey, I didn’t understand why so many homesteaders also focused on developing their primitive skills. For us, this transformation was about using existing resources to make a transition to something more sustainable without being uncomfortable. The longer we are on this path though, the more we realize that in order to make ourselves self-sufficient people we need a total mind-shift from the mentality of consumerism. I am beginning to see how learning primitive skills, and being able to conceive of living with a pre-industrial perspective, can help free us from the trap of believing that everything we consider normal these days is necessary in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t unravel healthcare when you believe it’s an entitlement and a necessity. You can’t end war in the Middle East when you see your life as dependent on fossil fuels. You can’t rail against the stock market when you support the underlying corporate systems with your purchase dollars. And we can’t keep one foot in both worlds and at the same time expect to live up to our ideals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if Matt and I will be building our own teepees or tanning a deer hide with brains any time soon, but we do plan to get back to more primitive ways by learning to live with fewer modern comforts. And we are planning to intentionally live on much less money than we currently use and see how far that limitation gets us towards truly becoming more self-sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That torrential drive here was a starting point. These last three years have been good preparation and training. We have a few more projects we’ve allowed on our list. Those will take financial resources, but will be wrapped up quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road beyond this last project list is unpaved, unknown, and likely to be much harder going, but we are totally looking forward to it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 04:09:59 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/04/03/three-years-in.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/04/03/three-years-in.html</guid>
        
        <category>homesteading</category>
        
        <category>subsistence</category>
        
        <category>anti-consumerism</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
        <category>essays</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Beauty of Transhuman Things</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was browsing through my Robinson Jeffers anthology yesterday evening before bed, reading one of his last poems, “Granddaughter,” when I was struck by a certain turn of phrase, as often happens with his poetry:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When she is eighteen \  I’ll not be here. I hope she will find her natural elements, \ Laughter and violence; and in her quiet times \ The beauty of things - the beauty of transhuman things, \ Without which we are all lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was that one line - &lt;em&gt;the beauty of things - the beauty of transhuman things&lt;/em&gt; - that grabbed me. The term &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transhumanism&quot;&gt;transhuman&lt;/a&gt; in these times suggests a notion of technologically enhanced human consciousness, quite different from what Jeffers had intended then. Transhumanism posits that consciousness will one day defy the mortal limits of our biology, ushering in the singularity, an event in which human consciousness essentially becomes data and merges with the artificial intelligence currently evolving out of our most advanced technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transhumanism as a term approaching the sense in which we understand it today, that is, as advanced by Ray Kurzweil and company, was first popularized in a 1957 essay by the biologist Julian Huxley, brother of Aldous and grandson of Thomas Henry Huxley, “Darwin’s Bulldog.” But Jeffers’ use of the term transhuman in one his last poems, probably written around the same time as Huxley’s essay, is diametrically opposed in most ways to our current understanding of that word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeffers devoted most of his work to developing what one might call a &lt;em&gt;poetics of the inhuman&lt;/em&gt; – An aesthetic theory and philosophy in which human history and human consciousness is not the sun around which everything else in nature revolves, but instead perhaps a distant moon, orbiting a planet defined by geologic timescales and natural forces beyond the grasp of any merely intellectual human understanding. These symbols of the inhuman are represented in his poetry by the ubiquitous granite that defines the Carmel coastline, as well as the house and tower he built by hand from granite and spent much of his life inhabiting; Or the sea itself, as it breaks down all things over time and represents the ur-womb from which terrestrial life emerged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… Meanwhile the image of the pristine beauty \ Lives in the very grain of the granite, \ Safe as the endless ocean that climbs our cliff.– As for us: \ We must uncenter our minds from ourselves; \ We must unhumanize our views a little, and become confident \ As the rock and ocean that we were made from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus concludes another of Jeffers’ later works “Carmel Point,” which had begun with the lament “This beautiful place defaced with a crop of suburban houses–”. Jeffers died in 1962, as America’s post-World War II expansion shifted into high gear. The years following the end of the war saw the rise of suburbia and the interstate system, the beginning in earnest of mass culture and the wholesale destruction of all things wild in the service of rampant consumerism and unfettered worldwide population growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeffers missed living through the Cuban Missile Crisis by almost a year, but as early as the 1930s he’d glimpsed the horrors of the world that has since come fully into view. In “The Purse Seine,” the poet has witnessed the spectacle of the sardine fishermen working the Pacific coast at night, sighting the phosphorescent clusters of fish and drawing in the net of the purse seine: “I cannot / tell you / How beautiful the scene is, and a little terrible, when the crowded fish / Know they are caught, and wildly beat from one wall to the other of their / closing destiny…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the poem turns, Jeffers is looking down from a mountain on a city at night and is reminded of the sardine fishing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…how could I help \ but recall the seine-net \ Gathering the luminous fish? I cannot tell you how beautiful 
the city \ appeared, and a little terrible. \ I thought, We have geared the machines and locked all together into \ interdependence; we have built the great cities; now \ There is no escape. We have gathered vast populations incapable of free survival, insulated \ From the strong earth, each person in himself helpless, on all dependent. \ The circle is closed, and the net \ Is being hauled in. They hardly feel the cords drawing, yet they shine \ already. The inevitable mass-disasters \ Will not come in our time nor in our children’s, but we and our children \&lt;br /&gt;
Must watch the net draw narrower, government take all powers –or \ revolution, and the new government \
Take more than all, add to kept bodies kept souls- or anarchy, the \
mass-disasters.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;These things are Progress;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the vantage point of 2017, it seems that Jeffers was remarkably prescient in his premonitions of the world awaiting his grand children’s generation. While we may not yet be truly living in the age of mass-disasters, they’re surely on the way. And though he could not have specifically anticipated climate change and its knock-on effects, thermonuclear warfare, genetic engineering, or the societal hazards of runaway computer and communications technologies, he surely understood the ramifications of population overshoot and the ensuing ecological collapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps more poignantly, he understood the dangers of the herd mentality, the hazards of a species enamored of its own image and multiplicity. In human terms, this amounts to the abandonment of our own wild nature and sense of place and belonging within nature for the aggregated culture of the anonymous cities and the soul crushing suburbs. This comes, of course, at the expense of our freedom, our independence, and our individual safety, in which we offer ourselves as “kept souls” on the altar of technology. Technology, that modern god born of human ingenuity, has only recently come to completely eclipse Gaia, the mother goddess from which we are all descended, in the pantheon of human wonder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so we find ourselves as a civilization at the outset of the Anthropocene, peering into our electronic oracles, if not with wonder, then with a hope tinged with desperation that technology will intervene in our favor to save us from ourselves, from the mass-disasters looming on the horizon. And the more fanatically deluded among us believe that technology will grant our souls - which we’ve already bartered away for the easy comforts of domesticity and the lure of progress - with everlasting life as data in some electronically emergent consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transhumanist agenda is the ultimate expression of a civilization beholden to a god of its own creation. If we can’t fix the problems that technology has created with technological solutions, for example geo-engineering to mitigate the consequences of climate change, then we’ll use our technology to find and inhabit other worlds. Or failing that, we’ll literally merge with our technologies once and for all and surrender our humanity, our biology, and our mortality to the technosphere, where our consciousness, if you can call it that, will live on forever in some virtualized simulacrum of the world we traded away for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biosphere, on the other hand, ailing as it is, represents an emergent consciousness that we are already embedded in, even as we actively or tacitly work to destroy it. James Lovelock and Lynn Margulis through Gaia theory have provided evidence that our seemingly inert geologic and atmospheric systems have co-evolved with the biological systems they sustain, seeking equilibrium through self-regulating feedback loops of greatcomplexity. These systems are composed not just of the biota that inhabit our planet, but of the seas and the rocks and the skies, those transhuman things as Jeffers perceived them, that through their interactions with each other on geological timescales exhibit a kind of emergent intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My recent reading of Dmitry Orlov’s &lt;em&gt;Shrinking the Technosphere&lt;/em&gt; has brought into sharp focus the antipathy of the technosphere towards the biosphere. It has become increasingly apparent to me as it has to others like Orlov that technology has a teleology of its own, that it has its own agenda and is using humanity in much the same sense as Richard Dawkins conception of the gene: That is, that human lives and bodies represent nothing more than survival machines for the gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology is the ultimate meme, a term that Dawkins invented, in his discussion from &lt;em&gt;The Selfish Gene&lt;/em&gt; to describe the concept of ideological self-reproduction. But the technosphere, as Orlov says in so many words, is bent on destroying all life, starting with that which can’t escape its net of quantification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is urgent now that we choose sides as partisans in this conflict between the technosphere and the biosphere. My loyalty is to Gaia and the beauty of truly transhuman things.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Mar 2017 04:09:59 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/03/23/the-beauty-of-transhuman-things.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/03/23/the-beauty-of-transhuman-things.html</guid>
        
        <category>robinson-jeffers</category>
        
        <category>transhumanism</category>
        
        <category>gaia-theory</category>
        
        <category>emergence</category>
        
        <category>ray-kurzweil</category>
        
        <category>inhumanism</category>
        
        <category>dmitry-orlov</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
        <category>essays</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to Our New(ly Updated) Blog</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome back to &lt;strong&gt;The Way Back&lt;/strong&gt;! It’s been a while since Tasha or I have updated the site. Part of the reason for this is because we have been in the process of migrating the site since the end of last summer, an admittedly drudgerous task, owing to the many photos and pages of text that required moving and reformatting…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now it’s done, and I’m really going to try to post more…really! One of the great things about this new site is that it’s quite a bit simpler than the previous one, a Drupal 7 site that was, quite frankly, overkill for the purposes of blogging. This is a Jekyll site that gets free hosting on Github, which amounts to a savings of about $300 a year in hosting fees. Cutting out our non-essential costs is a big deal for Tasha and me, and one of our major resolutions for this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the major improvements include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cleaner design with better typography&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Site is totally functional on any device or monitor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blog archive is organized by tags and content categories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social sharing buttons (Twitter, Facebook, Pinterest) make it easy to spread the good word&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll probably add a few separate areas to the site - maybe a photo gallery or something, perhaps a comments section - but we really want the focus of this site to be on our writing. Since we started blogging a few years ago, both Tasha and I have been writing quite a lot. Tasha has worked with &lt;em&gt;Mother Earth News&lt;/em&gt; and The Grow Network and &lt;em&gt;Grit&lt;/em&gt; magazine to share some of her practical knowledge of animal husbandry and horticulture, which has been rapidly evolving since we started here, just about three years ago now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been busy with my job and working on the farm, and when I have the free time, with writing in the form that I enjoy most, which is typically writing long essays. Over the past few years, I’ve been fortunate to have my work published on several occasions with &lt;a href=&quot;http://dark-mountain.net/&quot;&gt;The Dark Mountain Project&lt;/a&gt;. I’m excited that my most recent piece, “Indicator Species,” will publish in their next issue, out in April 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also done a couple more practically minded pieces for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://https://lowtechinstitute.org/2017/03/09/diy-project-making-a-broadfork-from-contributor-matt-miles/&quot;&gt;Low Technology Institute&lt;/a&gt; on building and using a broadfork, a tool I built for Tasha as a project utilizing my newly-acquired metalworking skills (I’ve been taking a welding class at the local community college).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Low Tech Institute is dedicated to providing information on all kinds of appropriate technologies and their practical implementation. With an academic slant and a new post daily, along with a lecture and podcast series, they are providing high-quality practical information on the rudimentary technologies necessary to support a civilization, the availability of which is often taken for granted in an increasingly fragile, disconnected, and technologically dependent society. You should go check them out - &lt;a href=&quot;https://lowtechinstitute.org/&quot;&gt;Low Technology Institute.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2017 04:09:59 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2017/03/15/welcome-to-the-new-way-back.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2017/03/15/welcome-to-the-new-way-back.html</guid>
        
        <category>the-dark-mountain-project</category>
        
        <category>the-low-tech-institute</category>
        
        <category>mother-earth-news</category>
        
        <category>the-grow-network</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ode to Matt</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hey y’all!  Today is Matt’s birthday. So, I thought I should put up an embarrassing gushing blog post about how wonderful he is.  Then I thought…probably nobody but me would want to read that.  So instead, I thought I’d put up an inventory of all the cool projects Matt has done here on the reLuxe Ranch.   In no specific order, here are just SOME of the amazing things Matt has contributed to us living the dream here on the reLuxe Ranch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/tTyFtbV.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt is the maker, maintainer, and harvester of the Asparagus patch (which is in fern state right now, storing energy in the roots for next year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/oVDzTOV.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt made our cats their own sandbox, which they failed to appreciate.  So he turned it into a turkey roost, which so far, only one of our turkeys has learned to use (through no fault of Matt’s perfect design). See how thoughtful he is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/GKRQYdw.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt installed our irrigation/aquaculture pond liner.  And he built these perfect chairs which we use for star gazing and cooling off after hot-tubbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/JXHJvzQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt built a platform for our hot tub, assembled the tub, and installed a chimney in the green house.  He also heats it for us almost nightly in fall, winter, and early spring.  This keeps our greenhouse plants happy and me too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/SyvUbQh.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh yes, and Matt built the greenhouse that holds the hot tub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/ewZkK7W.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt made our pig shelter with rain barrel for water collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/MkzhF6D.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt put up our slaughter stand for scalding pigs. The area also now doubles as my duck slaughter station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/PapDV2w.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt, with a little help from his brother and our friends, made us this awesome smoker which we use for our hams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/HbhxprA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve had a few challenges keeping bees and hope to get back to it next year.  But Matt made us awesome top bar bee hives designed to support bees natural hive tendencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/esTtMGB.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt did most of the heavy hauling for our hyper productive hugelcultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/6hIyv6X.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt spruced up my terracing and erosion prevention systems with decorative rail ties and built steps into our paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/SfVqh7A.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also gave us a nice shortcut from our back door to the solar container and work areas using rail ties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/zP4KhwT.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He made me a nice laundry line just out the door from the washer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/kF5bSWn.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He trellised our backyard vineyard so that we can eventually make our own yummy wines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/IICYuZd.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the help of Ted (chainsaw master) and our neighbors Donnie and Anita, Matt maintains 200+ shiitake logs in our mushroom grotto.  His mushrooms have been a staple food for us this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/ETXRzo5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He made us this gorgeous Mount Airy granite herb spiral that is so productive I  have to mutilate the plants multiple times a year to keep the growth in check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/5AvjlIp.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He made us this outdoor living room area and routinely makes me amazing cocktails to enjoy while relaxing in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/lL25SSj.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He made me my dream farm table that seats 14 comfortably so we can host our friends and family often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/PTrYPgu.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt created this incredible wood-fired pizza oven and makes the best sourdough pizza crust to cook in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/vYJP77r.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And his most recent project, is a climbing wall to keep us both in good shape for climbing and other activities and to share even more good times with friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can see for yourselves why Matt deserves an ode on his birthday.   But, as amazing as all this stuff is, the real reason he gets an ode is for all the stuff that’s not stuff. The way he cares for me, his constant support, being my rock when my dad had a stroke, letting me unload on him when the world is too much, and a million other kindness. Thank you Matt for everything! I love you. Happy birthday.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 04:09:59 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2016/10/26/ode-to-matt.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2016/10/26/ode-to-matt.html</guid>
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
