<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Way Back</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://the-way-back.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://the-way-back.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 18:24:47 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 18:24:47 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Slaughter Day: Part 1, Slaughtering and Scalding Pigs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A month ago, Tasha and I and several friends spent a long weekend immersed in what has come to be for us an annual event - slaughering our pigs. It’s never a day we look forward to especially, but when the days grow short and the overnight temperatures dip into the 30s, our thoughts turn to planning the pig slaughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year as in past years, our main concern has been to dispatch each pig as painlessly and humanely as possible. The Wendell Berry poem, “For the Hog Killing,” has become for us a sort of invocation at slaughter time, as well as a standard to uphold: “let them die while the sound of the shot is in the air, let them die as they fall.” In other words, as one commentator on the poem has put it, let the slaughter take place “with a minimum of violence.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tasha and I respect the lives of all the animals we care for, maybe even more so the ones we know we will eventually have to slaughter. LIke all the pigs we’ve raised, we cared for these from the time we brought them onto our farm as piglets until, over the course of the better part of a year, they’d grown to almost 400 pounds. Unlike past years, these piglets were obtained from our friends and neighbors Donnie and Anita Collins, whose breeding pair of Berkshires had produced these three males.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the time we moved them onto our farm in early spring, the pigs had as carefree a life as we were able to manage for them, never wanting for food, water or shelter, and having almost an acre of paddock to root and forage on. When the heat set in over the summer, we provided them with a wallow, watching them roll happily in the mud or doze in the shade of a thicket of bushes and trees. They had a good life here indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Joel Salatin has famously said, “So what if the pig has one bad day?” But we have endeavored to eliminate even that one bad day, slaughtering here on our farm instead of having it done at a commercial abbatoir. Ideally, the pig is shot in the forehead with a .22 rifle while feeding and then loses consciousness from the shot. While unconcious, his jugular vein or carotid artery is immediately severed with a stroke of the knife, and within seconds or a minute or two at most, succumbs from loss of blood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bleeding a pig is a necessary part of processing pork and recovering edible meat. With this in mind, it is also crucial to the process on practical as well as ethical grounds that the pig not be stressed or frightened before the slaughter, as the stress hormones that are rapidly dispersed into the pig’s bloodstream can sour the meat. This is just one more reason to carry out the slaughter with the utmost care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year our friend Tom, an avid hunter, offered to be our shooter. He expertly took down each pig with a carefully placed shot to the forehead, straight between the eyes and about an inch or so up. For full effect, the shot must be placed perpendicular to the pig’s skull. This is trickier than it would seem, even at point-blank range, because the pigs are constantly moving around and jockeying for position to get closest to the food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the first pig–our largest–went over at the shot, I hopped the wires of the electric fence and stuck it in the neck with a very sharp boning knife. I swept the knife blade up and back until blood gushed forth in a thick stream, alerting me that I’d cut the right the vein. This pig was so large that I had some difficulty getting my arm around its neck to the spot where i needed to plant the knife, though I did quickly find it and make the cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the next two pigs, I opted to make the stick almost at the breast and closer to the heart, a technique I’d seen done before, but one with which I had less practice. The cut involves sticking the knife in just above the pig’s breastplate and sweeping the knifeblade under to sever the carotid artery just above the heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/HMPQP9J.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;Tools of the Trade: Butcher Knife, Boning Knife and Straight Razor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With either of the two techniques, whether severing the jugular vein or carotid artery at the neck, or the carotid artery closer to the heart, a quick and humane death and a good bleed are ensured, if done properly. Having now gained more experience with the second technique, I feel it is the better way to go, especially with larger animals with a lot of fat around the jowl and neck, which makes locating the right spot in the neck a little more difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to avoid the repetitious description of the identical process involved in scalding and butchering each slaughtered pig, I’ll try rather to encapsulate and summarize the salient details and describe the process more abstractly from here on. I will also note that from shooting and sticking to splitting the carcass takes us on average about two hours for each pig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When each pig had finished bleeding out and we were certain that it was no longer alive, we attached ropes to its feet and dragged it the twenty-odd feet to our 4” x 6” crossbeam where we had hung a couple of engine hoists suspended over a scalding vat a little more than half full of 150-degree water. It’s important to leave room in the tank for the water the carcass will displace. No one likes to be burned by overflowing water as the pig is lowered into the tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tank, incidentally, started life as a heating oil tank before it was used as a stock tank on a local farm. It was brought to us by our friend Ted the first year we slaughtered pigs because we had trouble finding a large enough tank we could safely heat. With a few welded modifications and a spigot to easily drain water from the bottom, we had a custom-built tank that would be big enough for our pigs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/HX9Obxo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;Scalding Station with Engine Hoists&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing the 60 gallons of water necessary to scald a pig up to 150 degrees and holding it there for the duration of the slaughter can be a challenge; it is sometimes the most time consuming part of preparing for a slaughter. Anticipating this, I now start the two propane burners that heat our scalding tank first thing in the morning–that is, around 5:00 AM if we are planning to start slaughtering at 9:00 AM. If the previous night’s lows dip into the 20s, there is frequently a layer of ice on the surface of the tank and the water will take several hours to reach temperature. One way we conserve heat is by covering the top of the tank with foam insulation board. If it is very windy we also try to enclose the underside of the tank where the burners are situated with cinder block, foam board or other insulative materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scalding and scraping is not a strictly necessary part of the process of butchering a pig. Like most other large animals, pigs can be skinned, and depending on your meat preferences and situation, this may be a better option for some. Since we prize our bacon cuts and hams above all else–the latter of which we turn into prosciutto or aged country ham–the skin is an important and necessary part for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the pig carcass transported as close to the scalding tank as possible, I use a very sharp boning knife to make cuts in each of the front and rear legs, between the bone and the strong, tight tendons just below the knee joints. This can be tricky work with a sharp knife, so slowly and carefully is the way to go here. When each set of cuts has been made, I insert a steel gambrel through both the front and the back legs. A gambrel (or singletree) is a sturdy hanger with curved, pointed tines on each end that fit through the slits in the legs. In the center of the gambrel is an eye for attaching a hook or connector at the end of a rope or chain with which to raise the carcass and lower it into the scalding tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/3iBZbQz.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;Tools of the Trade: Spring Scale, Gambrel, Boning Hook, Bell Scraper, Bone Saw&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the months before we first slaughtered pigs in 2015, I built a crossbeam from several lengths of pressure-treated 4” x 6” beams (see first photo). Two uprights set in concrete and braced diagonally at the base where they contact the ground suspend a horizontal beam about 10 feet in the air. The height is necessary to clear the top of the tank with the length of the vertically suspended pig. With the hope of scalding two pigs at a time (impractical as I now know), I drilled through the top of the crossbeam in two places and attached a heavy-duty eyebolt through each hole. From each eyebolt, we hang an engine hoist, which is simply a racheting, locking, geared pulley that provides a significant mechanical advantage for lifting a heavy object overhead. Pulling a chain loop attached to the gears either raises or lowers the attached object… very slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the front gambrel hooked to a chain attached to the engine hoist, one person pulls on the chain loop and begins ratcheting the carcass up and forward into the scalding tank, while at least two others hold onto the rear gambrel running through the back legs and steer the back half of the carcass up and over the rim of the scalding tank, carefully placing it into the hot water. Since the mass of the pig carcass will quickly absorb heat and lower the water temperature, it’s not a bad idea to heat the water hotter (155 or even 160 degrees) than the target temperature of 150 degrees, keeping in mind that contacting the flesh of the pig with the possibly overheated metal of the scalding tank may set the hair follicle, making it impossible to remove with a scraper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, we typically run at least three lengths of chain across the width of the scalding tank. With these in place, between the bottom of the tank and the mass of the carcass, people on either side can pull the chains, thus rotating the carcass and keeping it from settling on the bottom of the tank. While several volunteers are employed agitating these chains, another dumps buckets of hot water across the exposed parts of the carcass such as the legs, which never fully submerge in the tank. Every minute or so, it’s a good idea to check the status of the hair by yanking on a tuft of it. When hair pulls easily from several places, usually after about five minutes of submersion in hot water, the carcass should be raised as quickly as possible from the water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, the pig carcass is now hanging vertically over the tank and completely out of the water. Working as quickly as possible, four people, each one armed with a bell scraper (basically a bell-shaped hemisphere of metal attached to a handle), begin working the flesh. Ideally, the movement of the rough edge of the scraper over the hair follicle removes the heat-loosened hairs relatively easily. In practice, there are usually some parts that require the hair be shaved off with a knife blade or straight razor. If there are large areas of the pig where the hair doesn’t scrape off easily, then it’s usually necessary to return the carcass for another dip in the scalding vat, again making sure not to set the hair follicles by overheating the tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When each pig has been satisfactorily scalded and scraped, the second hoist comes into play as a means of lowering out, or transferring in tandem with the first hoist, the pig carcass onto a hanging spring scale attached to the second hoist, where it is weighed and processed further. Weighing is not strictly necessary either, but we like to collect as much data as possible to assess our feed-to-meat ratio, figure out our cost per pound, and so forth, and hanging weight is a key metric in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the pig now hanging on the second engine hoist and safely away from the scalding vat, we note the weight and lower it to a comforatble working height and begin the process of evisceration, which I will describe in detail in the second part of this series of posts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2018 02:09:59 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2018/01/16/pig-slaughter.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2018/01/16/pig-slaughter.html</guid>
        
        <category>pigs</category>
        
        <category>slaughtering</category>
        
        <category>butchering</category>
        
        <category>ethical-meat</category>
        
        <category>Wendell-Berry</category>
        
        <category>Joel-Salatin</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>At Rest, At Last</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year, everyone, and may 2018 be your best year yet! The second day of the new year finds Tasha and me taking it easy after what seems like a non-stop three weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around the middle of December, we began preparing for our pig slaughter and all that entails - getting together suppies, unpacking tools and equipment, checking our friends’ availability to help with the slaughter, processing, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m planning on posting a series on the pig slaughter in its entirety later, but suffice it to say we had a couple good days of weather, the help of a few amazing friends, and the better part of a week’s worth of solid work processing well over a thousand pounds of pork (live weight).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following weekend was Christmas, which kept us busy as usual for the next few days with family events and visits. It was a wonderful holiday and a great time to be together with family, several of whom traveled to North Carolina to spend the holiday at my parents’ house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between Christmas and New Year’s, we hosted two very gracious cousins from South Carolina, who were interested in touring our farm and discussing sustainable agriculture with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, we spent most of a day helping some good friends in Virginia with their final chicken slaughter of the year, as the cold wave that has been menacing the eastern third of the US since shortly after Christmas intensified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent much of the afternoon on New Year’s Eve preparing to host a few friends for a small New Year’s party, which went off very well. Tasha and I were thrilled to celebrate the New Year with a great group of friends, some of whom we haven’t seen in many months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyle and Nicole, who are also neighbors and who run nearby York Farm, announced the upcoming release of the film,&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ragtagtribe.com/beulahland/&quot;&gt;“Somewhere in Beulah Land,” &lt;/a&gt; by filmmaker Andrew Brown that will document a year of life on their farm. Tasha and I are thrilled for them and can’t wait to catch the premiere in Winston-Salem next month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After making it to dawn and then sleeping for a few hours, we spent much of New Year’s Day with our good friends Matthew and Jenna, who are likely moving back to the west coast in a few weeks. We’ll really miss them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we rounded out the day with dinner at my folks’ house: black-eyed peas and collard greens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With what feels like almost three weeks of non-stop excitement and activity coming to an end, it feels good to spend some time catching up on sleep, reading, and just generally enjoying a few days of rest before diving into a long list of projects for the new year. It’s too cold to do much outside now anyway!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 02:09:59 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2018/01/02/at-rest-at-last.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2018/01/02/at-rest-at-last.html</guid>
        
        <category>daily</category>
        
        <category>updates</category>
        
        <category>documentary</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Geminids</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Tasha and I watched the Geminids meteor shower last night. Since it was also a very cold night here in North Carolina, we combined our skywatching with dips in the hot tub, which we use to heat our greenhouse on nights when it gets down into the 20s or below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We typically soak in the hot tub for as long as we can stand and then cool off on the Adirondack chairs I built for this purpose a couple years ago, which sit just outside the greenhouse on the rim of the upper pond. After the Russian fashion, we alternate between extremes of hot and cold. Usually, this is just the thing to guarantee a wonderful night’s sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From where the chairs are, our property forms a sort of bowl, with the whole sky falling away in every direction. While it’s certainly no dark-sky area, the closest big cities are many miles away and even on a mediocre night, the Milky Way is usually faintly visible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I was a kid, I’ve been fascinated with the night sky, astronomy, cosmology, and celstial events. It’s only recently though, mostly in the years since we’ve moved onto the farm, that I’ve thought much about what it means to be human in relation to the night and the heavens above. I’ve written about this elsewhere (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.humansandnature.org/endarkenment&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;  and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.garrisoninstitute.org/blog/seen-unseen/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), and It’s a subject that I find myself returning to frequently, as our future here on our terrestrial home seems less and less certain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night we did see a few spectacular meteors, though by no means the 120 per hour forecast to occur at the peak (2:00 AM). We were watching between 8:00 and 9:00 PM, but the meteors we saw - at least 10 of them - were remarkable in their brightness and intensity, leaving long, luminescent trails as they streaked across the dome of night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between soaking in 110-degree water and cooling off in the brisk, near-freezing night air while watching the light show in the skies above, something in me was satisfied, and I slept better than I have in months.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2017 02:09:59 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/12/14/Geminids.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/12/14/Geminids.html</guid>
        
        <category>updates</category>
        
        <category>daily</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
        <category>essays</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Enough Time</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Shortly after I posted the most recent update on this blog, I decided to quit my job, in April 2017. This decision had been a long time coming, and seven months later, I find I still have no regrets about making it. While spending less and living on more that comes directly from our farm has taken some getting used to, I feel like I’ve mostly adjusted. I’m truly comfortable with the idea of having more time while earning less money. Oddly enough though, after freeing up 40 plus hours a week from my mostly work-from-home job, I soon found that I had seemingly less time than I did before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, I had vowed to take a few months off before diving into any major projects, spending as much of the late spring and early summer months as I could in the outdoors - hiking, climbing, running, etc. I spent most of May working around the farm trying to knock off a “short” list of relatively minor projects, like fixing the leak in the roof, doing a major cleanup around the farm before the arrival of out-of-town visitors, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the weather began to turn really nice, I did manage to spend a lot of time running. One week, I did 48 miles on the Blue Ridge Parkway. But soon after that, my achilles tendon began really bothering me, so I had to give up the running for a while. When it hadn’t recovered after about a month, I decided to spend one day a week doing some serious mileage hiking. For much of July and August, that’s what I did every Monday when the weather would cooperate. It was definitely easier on my body than the running, but the achilles tendon is still bothering me, in spite of several attempts at rehabilitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the summer, I found myself spending many of my Wednesdays helping a friend cut vegetables and prepare and jar ferments in her kitchen. Most Thursdays, I spent much of the day in my own kitchen, preparing baked goods for Tasha to sell at the Friday farmers market. I also set out on some more ambitious long term projects. One of these was building out the existing space of the bouldering wall I completed in the summer of 2016 to incorporate a sort of tiny house – a mixed-use space of about 128 square feet that is now completely enclosed and will eventually have its own power supply (when I get around to installing our spare 400-Watt PV system).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so along with doing some of the routine growing season maintenance and a few smaller writing projects, I found my time mostly accounted for as summer turned to fall. With the holidays fast approaching, I’m not quite sure where fall went either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the days grow shorter and shorter and the cold settles in, I’ve been doing a lot of reading and finally feeling that I’m ready to commit to some of the more ambitious writing projects that have been kicking around in my head for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Tasha and I first embarked on this adventure almost four years ago now, I had in my mind what I’m sure is a much-idealized vision of living like Wendell Berry as a poet/writer/farmer; of retreating to the woods like Henry David Thoreau or Joseph Campbell, to read, write, and think about it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as the year draws to a close and I begin to find a balance between contemplative pursuits and all of the other responsibilities, distractions, and detours I’ve found myself engaged with since April, I’m once again commiting to regularly maintaining this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More and more, I’ve come to see the importance of having a daily writing practice, and I hope to incorporate this blog as part of that. Moving forward, I’m not sure what form my posts will take. I’m less interested now in describing the projects we are working on here or in providing the typical prosaic updates about how we’ve spent our time since the last blog post. We’ll see what form they take, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s good to feel like I finally have enough time.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 02:09:59 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/12/12/enough-time.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/12/12/enough-time.html</guid>
        
        <category>updates</category>
        
        <category>daily</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
        <category>essays</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Three Years In: A Self-Assessment and the Work to Come</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, in the midst of a torrential downpour - Matt in the moving truck, me in my Honda Fit, and my dad in his car - we made our way from the suburbs of Washington, D.C. to our new home in rural North Carolina. The traffic around D.C. and Northern Virginia was horrendous, with accidents littering the roadways every few miles. Despite the total lack of visibility and flooded pockets of pavement, drivers were cutting each other off to get a few feet ahead, driving too fast when the traffic picked up, and slamming on their brakes repeatedly as if they were intentionally hoping to cause an accident too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As sad as I was about leaving our friends and family, that drive to our new life had felt like an affirmation of all the reasons why change was necessary. When we finally made it to Lowgap, I remember having a great sense of relief. It wasn’t just because we survived the drive, but that we had actually done “it.” We said goodbye to a way of living that felt destructive and silly but somehow stable, and had taken our first step towards something we hoped would be meaningful and regenerative, but that was also far more speculative than the beaten path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the days that followed, that sense of relief gave way to a question that we are effectively still trying to answer three years later. We had all sorts of plans about what our life here would look like. We’d studied a bunch of books, visited farms, talked to farmers, watched videos, made notes, and planned projects. As we started developing our food systems and installing infrastructure, it became clear that we had a made a pretty good road map for how to transform our landscape, but we hadn’t thought much about what it would take to be kind of people to best inhabit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite our progress, we have not yet answered the question “How do we become self-sufficient people?”
I’ve spent most of my life thinking that solutions came from stores, answers were out there, and professionals are necessary because I am only qualified to handle certain things on my own. One of the side-effects of a consumer culture is that our knowledge and skills have been narrowed down to what we get paid for and are considered qualified to do. We’ve become our jobs and our degrees, rather than a citizenry of well-rounded people with a high level of autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, our initial challenge has been to overcome those market dependencies by gaining skills through doing and developing effective replacement systems. To date, we’ve spent much of our time here experimenting, reading, trying, failing, improving, and eventually succeeding in the following areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing our own food in a greenhouse, in an annual garden, in food forests, on hugelkulturs, using aquaculture, with the use of livestock, mushroom cultivation, foraging, etc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building structures like animal shelters, a smokehouse, a pizza oven, and a greenhouse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Installing fences to keep some animals in and others out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Water management – e.g., pond building, swales, hugelkulturs, diversion channels, rain depressions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ecological restoration and wildlife and pollinator habitat creation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building community&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Food preparation – cheese, vinegar, wine, fermented foods, bread, pizza, etc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing a mix of homestead products for sale to local markets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Miscellaneous skills like welding for Matt and soap-making for Tasha&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Writing about our experiences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, the more skilled we become, the more we understand that it isn’t just our loss of skills that inures us to the system - it’s the very way we frame our questions and answers. We think in terms of goods and services. We are habituated to transactional living. And our choices are colored by addiction to products and services that we can’t, and shouldn’t try to, reproduce at the homestead level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is evident that even our notions of what constitutes problems, and how we go about solving them, stems from consumer culture. For example, a while back, our dishwasher broke. My first thought was, we’ll have to buy a new one. But then I reminded myself I was now a competent homesteader and should try to fix it. I tried and failed. Matt and I contemplated whether we really needed a dishwasher. We can’t run it on solar panels. We know it’s not sustainable. But the alternative of hand-washing when we have limited counter space, painfully shallow sinks, and use so many dishes for all food preparation activities seemed unmanageable with all our other time commitments. We decided a new dishwasher was a luxury, but one that we would indulge in for now and try to wean ourselves from down the road. We effectively did a cost benefit analysis and chose perceived convenience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I say “perceived” because when framed in the context of becoming self-sufficient people, it was a totally wrong answer. We’re now newly invested in an expensive technology that requires the use of electricity that we cannot generate ourselves. Regardless of the propaganda by dishwasher advocates, we know it is far more energy efficient to do dishes by filling a small tub of soapy water for washing and scrubbing and just rinsing quickly under running water. And the fact that we use so many dishes is an indication that we still have some simplification to do to become self-sufficient. A new dishwasher isn’t a convenience on the road to self-sufficiency, it’s a lengthy and unnecessary detour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dishwasher is an expensive item and obviously not sustainable, so it’s an easy example to point to. The real challenges though are not in the big decisions; we know the right answers on those even if we choose otherwise. The small and daily decisions have a larger cumulative effect than a one-time purchase of a dishwasher. And these, are in fact the habits we find most difficult to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started this adventure with the notion that we would use the easy availability of consumer products to fast-track our way to self-sufficiency. And that philosophy has served us well to a point. But now we need to make the next step in our transition and cut our ties to consumer culture, even if it feels like a hardship until we adjust. In truth, we don’t know exactly what this looks like because we have not seen it in our lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt and I both have early memories of being marketed to as children watching Saturday morning cartoons or re-runs of The Dukes of Hazard. If you doubt the pervasiveness of the messages, then think back to your favorite toy. Was it home-made or store bought? How long was it your favorite? How many other toys did you have? If are in the forty-something age bracket (like us), did you have a big wheel or a cabbage patch doll, or know someone who did? There’s a high probability that many of you in our age range have similar memories and experiences. And that’s not just a coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though Matt and I both rebelled in our youth becoming “alternative,” we each have stories of owning Creepers and Doc Martens, and other similar brand-named alternative attire. That too is not an accident. Fashion took over punk rock before we knew it existed. Nearly anything that starts as an authentic movement eventually gets co-opted by the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now with the internet, marketing has become even more pervasive and directed. As I click through websites on homesteading, animal husbandry, building a gray water system, composting toilet, DIY anything… related ads start to pop-up. Recently I was reading a post on “What Homesteading Really Costs…” I could only read a short section without scrolling because most of the screen was covered by advertisements for chicken coops and cattle panels (since I’d recently been searching those). In the post, the author wrote about having to pay for fences, roads, rebuilding structures, how she started blogging to make some money, but then she became an essential oils saleswoman and her husband was able to quit his job and build their dream home. And you can become a sales rep too, and support her dream of homesteading, while also supporting yours…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that the idea of the self-sufficient life has now also been usurped by advertising and an alternative product list. But Matt and I don’t want a simulacrum of a self-sufficient life. We genuinely want to opt out, not just to buy into an alternate version. And we know the only real way to do that is to learn to live without spending money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we first started this journey, I didn’t understand why so many homesteaders also focused on developing their primitive skills. For us, this transformation was about using existing resources to make a transition to something more sustainable without being uncomfortable. The longer we are on this path though, the more we realize that in order to make ourselves self-sufficient people we need a total mind-shift from the mentality of consumerism. I am beginning to see how learning primitive skills, and being able to conceive of living with a pre-industrial perspective, can help free us from the trap of believing that everything we consider normal these days is necessary in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t unravel healthcare when you believe it’s an entitlement and a necessity. You can’t end war in the Middle East when you see your life as dependent on fossil fuels. You can’t rail against the stock market when you support the underlying corporate systems with your purchase dollars. And we can’t keep one foot in both worlds and at the same time expect to live up to our ideals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if Matt and I will be building our own teepees or tanning a deer hide with brains any time soon, but we do plan to get back to more primitive ways by learning to live with fewer modern comforts. And we are planning to intentionally live on much less money than we currently use and see how far that limitation gets us towards truly becoming more self-sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That torrential drive here was a starting point. These last three years have been good preparation and training. We have a few more projects we’ve allowed on our list. Those will take financial resources, but will be wrapped up quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road beyond this last project list is unpaved, unknown, and likely to be much harder going, but we are totally looking forward to it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 04:09:59 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/04/03/three-years-in.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/04/03/three-years-in.html</guid>
        
        <category>homesteading</category>
        
        <category>subsistence</category>
        
        <category>anti-consumerism</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
        <category>essays</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Beauty of Transhuman Things</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was browsing through my Robinson Jeffers anthology yesterday evening before bed, reading one of his last poems, “Granddaughter,” when I was struck by a certain turn of phrase, as often happens with his poetry:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When she is eighteen \  I’ll not be here. I hope she will find her natural elements, \ Laughter and violence; and in her quiet times \ The beauty of things - the beauty of transhuman things, \ Without which we are all lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was that one line - &lt;em&gt;the beauty of things - the beauty of transhuman things&lt;/em&gt; - that grabbed me. The term &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transhumanism&quot;&gt;transhuman&lt;/a&gt; in these times suggests a notion of technologically enhanced human consciousness, quite different from what Jeffers had intended then. Transhumanism posits that consciousness will one day defy the mortal limits of our biology, ushering in the singularity, an event in which human consciousness essentially becomes data and merges with the artificial intelligence currently evolving out of our most advanced technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transhumanism as a term approaching the sense in which we understand it today, that is, as advanced by Ray Kurzweil and company, was first popularized in a 1957 essay by the biologist Julian Huxley, brother of Aldous and grandson of Thomas Henry Huxley, “Darwin’s Bulldog.” But Jeffers’ use of the term transhuman in one his last poems, probably written around the same time as Huxley’s essay, is diametrically opposed in most ways to our current understanding of that word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeffers devoted most of his work to developing what one might call a &lt;em&gt;poetics of the inhuman&lt;/em&gt; – An aesthetic theory and philosophy in which human history and human consciousness is not the sun around which everything else in nature revolves, but instead perhaps a distant moon, orbiting a planet defined by geologic timescales and natural forces beyond the grasp of any merely intellectual human understanding. These symbols of the inhuman are represented in his poetry by the ubiquitous granite that defines the Carmel coastline, as well as the house and tower he built by hand from granite and spent much of his life inhabiting; Or the sea itself, as it breaks down all things over time and represents the ur-womb from which terrestrial life emerged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… Meanwhile the image of the pristine beauty \ Lives in the very grain of the granite, \ Safe as the endless ocean that climbs our cliff.– As for us: \ We must uncenter our minds from ourselves; \ We must unhumanize our views a little, and become confident \ As the rock and ocean that we were made from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus concludes another of Jeffers’ later works “Carmel Point,” which had begun with the lament “This beautiful place defaced with a crop of suburban houses–”. Jeffers died in 1962, as America’s post-World War II expansion shifted into high gear. The years following the end of the war saw the rise of suburbia and the interstate system, the beginning in earnest of mass culture and the wholesale destruction of all things wild in the service of rampant consumerism and unfettered worldwide population growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeffers missed living through the Cuban Missile Crisis by almost a year, but as early as the 1930s he’d glimpsed the horrors of the world that has since come fully into view. In “The Purse Seine,” the poet has witnessed the spectacle of the sardine fishermen working the Pacific coast at night, sighting the phosphorescent clusters of fish and drawing in the net of the purse seine: “I cannot / tell you / How beautiful the scene is, and a little terrible, when the crowded fish / Know they are caught, and wildly beat from one wall to the other of their / closing destiny…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the poem turns, Jeffers is looking down from a mountain on a city at night and is reminded of the sardine fishing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…how could I help \ but recall the seine-net \ Gathering the luminous fish? I cannot tell you how beautiful 
the city \ appeared, and a little terrible. \ I thought, We have geared the machines and locked all together into \ interdependence; we have built the great cities; now \ There is no escape. We have gathered vast populations incapable of free survival, insulated \ From the strong earth, each person in himself helpless, on all dependent. \ The circle is closed, and the net \ Is being hauled in. They hardly feel the cords drawing, yet they shine \ already. The inevitable mass-disasters \ Will not come in our time nor in our children’s, but we and our children \&lt;br /&gt;
Must watch the net draw narrower, government take all powers –or \ revolution, and the new government \
Take more than all, add to kept bodies kept souls- or anarchy, the \
mass-disasters.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;These things are Progress;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the vantage point of 2017, it seems that Jeffers was remarkably prescient in his premonitions of the world awaiting his grand children’s generation. While we may not yet be truly living in the age of mass-disasters, they’re surely on the way. And though he could not have specifically anticipated climate change and its knock-on effects, thermonuclear warfare, genetic engineering, or the societal hazards of runaway computer and communications technologies, he surely understood the ramifications of population overshoot and the ensuing ecological collapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps more poignantly, he understood the dangers of the herd mentality, the hazards of a species enamored of its own image and multiplicity. In human terms, this amounts to the abandonment of our own wild nature and sense of place and belonging within nature for the aggregated culture of the anonymous cities and the soul crushing suburbs. This comes, of course, at the expense of our freedom, our independence, and our individual safety, in which we offer ourselves as “kept souls” on the altar of technology. Technology, that modern god born of human ingenuity, has only recently come to completely eclipse Gaia, the mother goddess from which we are all descended, in the pantheon of human wonder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so we find ourselves as a civilization at the outset of the Anthropocene, peering into our electronic oracles, if not with wonder, then with a hope tinged with desperation that technology will intervene in our favor to save us from ourselves, from the mass-disasters looming on the horizon. And the more fanatically deluded among us believe that technology will grant our souls - which we’ve already bartered away for the easy comforts of domesticity and the lure of progress - with everlasting life as data in some electronically emergent consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transhumanist agenda is the ultimate expression of a civilization beholden to a god of its own creation. If we can’t fix the problems that technology has created with technological solutions, for example geo-engineering to mitigate the consequences of climate change, then we’ll use our technology to find and inhabit other worlds. Or failing that, we’ll literally merge with our technologies once and for all and surrender our humanity, our biology, and our mortality to the technosphere, where our consciousness, if you can call it that, will live on forever in some virtualized simulacrum of the world we traded away for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biosphere, on the other hand, ailing as it is, represents an emergent consciousness that we are already embedded in, even as we actively or tacitly work to destroy it. James Lovelock and Lynn Margulis through Gaia theory have provided evidence that our seemingly inert geologic and atmospheric systems have co-evolved with the biological systems they sustain, seeking equilibrium through self-regulating feedback loops of greatcomplexity. These systems are composed not just of the biota that inhabit our planet, but of the seas and the rocks and the skies, those transhuman things as Jeffers perceived them, that through their interactions with each other on geological timescales exhibit a kind of emergent intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My recent reading of Dmitry Orlov’s &lt;em&gt;Shrinking the Technosphere&lt;/em&gt; has brought into sharp focus the antipathy of the technosphere towards the biosphere. It has become increasingly apparent to me as it has to others like Orlov that technology has a teleology of its own, that it has its own agenda and is using humanity in much the same sense as Richard Dawkins conception of the gene: That is, that human lives and bodies represent nothing more than survival machines for the gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology is the ultimate meme, a term that Dawkins invented, in his discussion from &lt;em&gt;The Selfish Gene&lt;/em&gt; to describe the concept of ideological self-reproduction. But the technosphere, as Orlov says in so many words, is bent on destroying all life, starting with that which can’t escape its net of quantification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is urgent now that we choose sides as partisans in this conflict between the technosphere and the biosphere. My loyalty is to Gaia and the beauty of truly transhuman things.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Mar 2017 04:09:59 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/03/23/the-beauty-of-transhuman-things.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2017/03/23/the-beauty-of-transhuman-things.html</guid>
        
        <category>robinson-jeffers</category>
        
        <category>transhumanism</category>
        
        <category>gaia-theory</category>
        
        <category>emergence</category>
        
        <category>ray-kurzweil</category>
        
        <category>inhumanism</category>
        
        <category>dmitry-orlov</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
        <category>essays</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to Our New(ly Updated) Blog</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome back to &lt;strong&gt;The Way Back&lt;/strong&gt;! It’s been a while since Tasha or I have updated the site. Part of the reason for this is because we have been in the process of migrating the site since the end of last summer, an admittedly drudgerous task, owing to the many photos and pages of text that required moving and reformatting…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now it’s done, and I’m really going to try to post more…really! One of the great things about this new site is that it’s quite a bit simpler than the previous one, a Drupal 7 site that was, quite frankly, overkill for the purposes of blogging. This is a Jekyll site that gets free hosting on Github, which amounts to a savings of about $300 a year in hosting fees. Cutting out our non-essential costs is a big deal for Tasha and me, and one of our major resolutions for this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the major improvements include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cleaner design with better typography&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Site is totally functional on any device or monitor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blog archive is organized by tags and content categories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social sharing buttons (Twitter, Facebook, Pinterest) make it easy to spread the good word&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll probably add a few separate areas to the site - maybe a photo gallery or something, perhaps a comments section - but we really want the focus of this site to be on our writing. Since we started blogging a few years ago, both Tasha and I have been writing quite a lot. Tasha has worked with &lt;em&gt;Mother Earth News&lt;/em&gt; and The Grow Network and &lt;em&gt;Grit&lt;/em&gt; magazine to share some of her practical knowledge of animal husbandry and horticulture, which has been rapidly evolving since we started here, just about three years ago now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been busy with my job and working on the farm, and when I have the free time, with writing in the form that I enjoy most, which is typically writing long essays. Over the past few years, I’ve been fortunate to have my work published on several occasions with &lt;a href=&quot;http://dark-mountain.net/&quot;&gt;The Dark Mountain Project&lt;/a&gt;. I’m excited that my most recent piece, “Indicator Species,” will publish in their next issue, out in April 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also done a couple more practically minded pieces for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://https://lowtechinstitute.org/2017/03/09/diy-project-making-a-broadfork-from-contributor-matt-miles/&quot;&gt;Low Technology Institute&lt;/a&gt; on building and using a broadfork, a tool I built for Tasha as a project utilizing my newly-acquired metalworking skills (I’ve been taking a welding class at the local community college).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Low Tech Institute is dedicated to providing information on all kinds of appropriate technologies and their practical implementation. With an academic slant and a new post daily, along with a lecture and podcast series, they are providing high-quality practical information on the rudimentary technologies necessary to support a civilization, the availability of which is often taken for granted in an increasingly fragile, disconnected, and technologically dependent society. You should go check them out - &lt;a href=&quot;https://lowtechinstitute.org/&quot;&gt;Low Technology Institute.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2017 04:09:59 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2017/03/15/welcome-to-the-new-way-back.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2017/03/15/welcome-to-the-new-way-back.html</guid>
        
        <category>the-dark-mountain-project</category>
        
        <category>the-low-tech-institute</category>
        
        <category>mother-earth-news</category>
        
        <category>the-grow-network</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ode to Matt</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hey y’all!  Today is Matt’s birthday. So, I thought I should put up an embarrassing gushing blog post about how wonderful he is.  Then I thought…probably nobody but me would want to read that.  So instead, I thought I’d put up an inventory of all the cool projects Matt has done here on the reLuxe Ranch.   In no specific order, here are just SOME of the amazing things Matt has contributed to us living the dream here on the reLuxe Ranch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/tTyFtbV.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt is the maker, maintainer, and harvester of the Asparagus patch (which is in fern state right now, storing energy in the roots for next year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/oVDzTOV.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt made our cats their own sandbox, which they failed to appreciate.  So he turned it into a turkey roost, which so far, only one of our turkeys has learned to use (through no fault of Matt’s perfect design). See how thoughtful he is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/GKRQYdw.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt installed our irrigation/aquaculture pond liner.  And he built these perfect chairs which we use for star gazing and cooling off after hot-tubbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/JXHJvzQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt built a platform for our hot tub, assembled the tub, and installed a chimney in the green house.  He also heats it for us almost nightly in fall, winter, and early spring.  This keeps our greenhouse plants happy and me too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/SyvUbQh.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh yes, and Matt built the greenhouse that holds the hot tub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/ewZkK7W.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt made our pig shelter with rain barrel for water collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/MkzhF6D.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt put up our slaughter stand for scalding pigs. The area also now doubles as my duck slaughter station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/PapDV2w.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt, with a little help from his brother and our friends, made us this awesome smoker which we use for our hams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/HbhxprA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve had a few challenges keeping bees and hope to get back to it next year.  But Matt made us awesome top bar bee hives designed to support bees natural hive tendencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/esTtMGB.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt did most of the heavy hauling for our hyper productive hugelcultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/6hIyv6X.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt spruced up my terracing and erosion prevention systems with decorative rail ties and built steps into our paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/SfVqh7A.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also gave us a nice shortcut from our back door to the solar container and work areas using rail ties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/zP4KhwT.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He made me a nice laundry line just out the door from the washer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/kF5bSWn.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He trellised our backyard vineyard so that we can eventually make our own yummy wines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/IICYuZd.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the help of Ted (chainsaw master) and our neighbors Donnie and Anita, Matt maintains 200+ shiitake logs in our mushroom grotto.  His mushrooms have been a staple food for us this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/ETXRzo5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He made us this gorgeous Mount Airy granite herb spiral that is so productive I  have to mutilate the plants multiple times a year to keep the growth in check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/5AvjlIp.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He made us this outdoor living room area and routinely makes me amazing cocktails to enjoy while relaxing in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/lL25SSj.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He made me my dream farm table that seats 14 comfortably so we can host our friends and family often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/PTrYPgu.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt created this incredible wood-fired pizza oven and makes the best sourdough pizza crust to cook in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/vYJP77r.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And his most recent project, is a climbing wall to keep us both in good shape for climbing and other activities and to share even more good times with friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can see for yourselves why Matt deserves an ode on his birthday.   But, as amazing as all this stuff is, the real reason he gets an ode is for all the stuff that’s not stuff. The way he cares for me, his constant support, being my rock when my dad had a stroke, letting me unload on him when the world is too much, and a million other kindness. Thank you Matt for everything! I love you. Happy birthday.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 04:09:59 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2016/10/26/ode-to-matt.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/2016/10/26/ode-to-matt.html</guid>
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Care and Feeding</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi Y’all! I am sorry it’s been so long since I posted anything on our blog. My dad had a totally unexpected stroke back on March 3 which has been life-changing for us. And honestly, I’ve been struggling to decide how to write about the experience.  I first wrote a long (of course) and critical post about our modern medical system and why I was an idiot for calling 911 and subjecting my dad to it.  I was at the final editing stage when I mentioned the subject to Matt over dinner.  With his usual candor, he replied, “Tasha, do you really think anyone wants to read about how broken our system is?” Since I had already painstakingly written 3343 words on the subject, he was lucky my wine glass was full or I would have hurled it at him.  But by the time we finished our talk and I emptied my glass, I realized he had a point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even writing about the experience made me angry. Recounting all the absurd and dangerous practices that qualify as “care” that cost patients and taxpayers ridiculous amounts of money probably increased my own risk of stroke.  Really though, I don’t want to be angry and I don’t want to write about things that will give other people reasons to be angry either.  Hate and anger make people crazy. Just look at all these race-based shootings by and/or at the police or the hate attacks in France and Florida. We don’t need more to be mad about.
Note: My original rant was not about the hardworking professionals who did their best for my dad, but about the way insurance, lawsuit-driven risk management procedures, pharmaceutical companies, and algorithms determine standards of care, the overuse of antibiotics, and the detriment of over-compartmentalized job descriptions and unnecessary administrative requirements burdening staff. Some of you hardworking medical professionals were my best advisors during this time because you know the challenges. Your hard work is appreciated especially now that I understand better what you have to deal with on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, here’s my alternative posting, thanks to Matt’s intervention…
My dad’s ten day hospital stint in Winston-Salem falls into the category of “shit happens”.  It’s behind us and thanks to the location of his brain hemorrhage, my dad can’t even remember being there.
And I feel extremely fortunate that Matt and I have managed to live our lives in a manner that made it possible for me to care for my dad at home after emergency treatment ended. Many people are forced to work too many hours and have too much stress built into their lives to be able to provide round-the-clock care for incapacitated loved ones. Some people have their own limiting health concerns and don’t have the physical stamina to care for someone else. Changing a 150 pound adult’s “diaper”, lifting them on and off the bedside toilet, massaging their body parts, giving them sponge baths, and moving their limbs to prevent muscle atrophy are time-consuming and highly physical tasks. If my dad’s stroke had happened a few years ago, when I worked in the legal world, I would not have been either physically or time-wise capable of handling those tasks.  But homesteading has helped me reclaim my physical health and prepared me to care for my dad in countless ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am really so thankful to have this “luxury”.  It may not seem like a luxury some days, but it’s exactly what we meant when we gave up our city lives and began to “reLuxe”.  We traded money for time.  And things for experiences. And I am so glad we did because our lives have become much richer in what matters as a result.&lt;br /&gt;
Humans like to think we’re a special and distinct from the rest of nature.  But I can tell you after months of taking care of  my dad, from a physical perspective our needs are fundamentally the same as an animal’s.  After the initial shock of his stroke and panic about what to do about it wore off, I realized that most of what I did for my dad was a perfect parallel to what I did for chickens, ducks, pigs, goats, and in some ways even worms and plants.  I make his meals, clean his area, put on TV programs I know he’ll like, take him out for fresh air and sunshine, occasionally take him to town for distraction, help him with grooming, to the degree to which he is capable, I teach him how to do things to make it easier on me to care for him, etc.
Humans need food, water, companionship, entertainment, and comfort.  We aim for the elimination of pain, distraction from it when elimination is impossible, and the illusion of safety.  On the Ranch, this is exactly what we provide for our animals.  When I write up my chore lists and daily duties, I lump these activities into a category called “Care and Feeding”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, we differ from animals in that we can brood over our plight and wallow in self-pity.  I have yet to see any of our farm animals do that.  And we can also transcend our experience and transform tragedies into new trajectories.
What happened to my dad is not really a tragedy, but more a normal part of life.  Others have suffered, or are still suffering, much worse for reasons that make no sense like hatred and greed.  It’s hard to see it this way when your life is transformed into something totally unrecognizable in a matter of hours.  But in fact our bodies are built to decay.  Our time, in this iteration of ourselves, is limited. We know this, but we seem to need to be reminded.  And I have been. Watching my dad face his struggles with humor when he didn’t even know his name, or realized he needed the restroom but couldn’t get there on time, or when he finally got the spoon to his mouth only to discover he forgot to load it, has been one of the most humanizing and heart-breakingly beautiful experiences of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My dad has always been one of my best friends.  I have sought his advice for all my struggles and have always eagerly shared successes with him, wanting him to be proud, not just of me, but of his own accomplishment in enabling mine. Some days I wish I could talk to him like I used to, but since his language skills are still a tangled mess, I can’t.  Even so, through his actions, the way he meets each day and each new obstacle (as there are literally thousands of things he has to relearn), he has perhaps demonstrated the most important lesson he will ever teach me.  I only hope that one day I’ll be able to face life with such grace.  And that’s what he has shown me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grace. The sublime gift of being, the simple elegance of meeting experiences honestly, and without anger. 
There are things we can change and things we can’t.  The past for example, that’s done and gone. Megalithic systems like “health care” and Wall Street are facts of our world.  To some extent we are stuck with them for now, though we can minimize use and work towards change.  Climate change is real and we must face it.  Whatever we are at our core, we are still clothed in skin, bones, blood, organs, and biology.  Our bodies are vehicles that wear out and eventually fail.  But we still have choices to make.  We can meet our realities as my dad has.  With grace.  Or we can waste our energy being angry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can choose grace or anger or shades between. This is what makes us human.  The rest, from my perspective, is just care and feeding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I owe a lot of people gratitude and appreciation for all their support through this time. We’re now getting a bit more traffic on our site thanks to some of our writings with Dark Mountain (Matt) and Mother Earth News and The Grow Network (Tasha), so in the interest of preserving everyone’s privacy, I won’t name you in this blog, but you know who you are. So, to those of you who suffered my angry rants while my dad was in the hospital - I’m sorry!  And thank you. You kept me sane. To those of you who have patiently listened while my dad chatted away about liver farts, fiddle faddles, and talked about himself as “her” and “she”,  as if you had any idea what he was trying to say, thank you.  You made me proud to call you friend. To those of you who cooked us food, visited us in the early days (when it was frankly painful to see), offered to take care of our animals or give Matt and I a night-off for a little romance, thank you.  You gave me hope that we could get through this.  We really are so lucky to be surrounded by such incredible community and family.  It honestly makes me wonder why we can’t solve the world’s problems when there are so many wonderful people in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On second thought…maybe we still can. At the very least, we can meet what comes with grace and in the company of good friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(And to Matt - You are too good to be true, and yet you prove with your actions and constant support that you are.  This is a paradox I may never unravel and yet am infinitely grateful for.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2016/07/27/care-and-feeding.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/blogs/essays/2016/07/27/care-and-feeding.html</guid>
        
        <category>healthcare</category>
        
        
        <category>blogs</category>
        
        <category>essays</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>reLuxe Mega Round Up - April 3, 2016</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Woo-hoo, time for another reLuxe (mega) Roundup! What makes this one a mega roundup, you might ask? Well, this one’s got lots of pictures (below the fold). Back when I started this blog, we were limited in how much we could store on the server. Now there’re no limits, and a picture’s worth a thousand words, so here we go.
It’s been a while since Tasha or I wrote one of these, and there have been quite a few changes in the intervening seven months here at the Ranch. After a relatively painless and short winter, here we are, having come out the other side, to an early spring. With temperatures reaching into the 70s for the past couple weeks and Daylight Savings Time once again in effect, it’s been easy for both of us to get outside and get things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2016-04-02-reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016/Woodford.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Woodford the Turkey&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 10 or so turkeys we have been raising since last summer, three remain. We haven’t slaughtered a single one—the others either didn’t make it to adulthood or died by misadventure (wandering off the farm and being chased by neighborhood dogs, we suspect). After losing our last two Slate Grays last month, Woodford—our Bourbon Red, and Ferdinand and Isabella—our two Spanish Blacks, have all essentially become pets.
They follow us around whenever we work outside and are much more curious and intrepid than our chickens and ducks. They’ve become the peacocks that Tasha always wanted, and they don’t do nearly as much damage due to scratching as chickens. All in all, they tend to forage pretty well, eat a lot of pests we don’t want around anyway, and don’t require much care, so they get to stay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our ducklings, however, hatched last month in an incubator from eggs our permanent Pekins laid, won’t be so lucky. By the end of spring, they’ll be slaughtered for meat, although they’ll enjoy an idyllic and stress-free life here in the meantime. They’ll be free to roam once they’re big enough to leave the greenhouse that they share with Maggie, the single chicken that hatched a few days before the ducks. Maggie—we think it’s a female—will join the other layers in the coop once she’s large enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2016-04-02-reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016/Ducklings.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Ducklings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her mother was obviously one of our Barred-Rocks, and her father’s identity could only be Roscoe, the rooster who just showed up one day over the winter and decided to move in with our hens. They seem to like him well enough, though we eventually found out he belongs to a neighbor who rescued him but didn’t have a place to keep him. Well, problem solved. We’ve sort of gotten used to him starting to crow at 4:00 AM, from the chicken coop, which is directly behind our bedroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the winter we also spent a few weeks smoking the country hams which were hanging in the shop to dry out for a few months prior. At the end of February, we spent about a week using peach, hickory, and red oak to smoke the hams of various sizes. The largest ones, probably in the 40-to-50 pound range, will take another year to cure before they’re ready to eat, although the smaller ones should probably be ready this year. The two prosciuttos packed in salt and curing in bee boxes will soon join the hams in the smokehouse to finish out the aging process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2016-04-02-reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016/Hams.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Hams in the smokehouse&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tasha has been busy with early spring starts like potatoes and transplanting cabbages from the greenhouse to the main garden. She’s also been planting another round of grape vines, fruit trees, shrubs, and perennials all around the property. The strawberries she planted last year are really taking off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2016-04-02-reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016/Cabbage Starts.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Cabbage Starts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2016-04-02-reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016/Strawberries.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Strawberries&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perennials planted last year and the year before seem to have mostly made it, and at the very least established their roots. Everything takes a little longer here, since there was essentially no topsoil on most of the property when we bought it. Some of our first intensively planted “food forest” groves—the areas adjacent to the outdoor dining area–are starting to take hold, in particular, the elderberry bushes, comfrey, yarrow, and goji berries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2016-04-02-reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016/Perennials.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Perennials&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In late March, we harvested our first crop of asparagus from our most recent (year-old) asparagus bed. Today shoots from the second-year bed, which I dug a little deeper, started to poke through the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2016-04-02-reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016/Asparagus.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Asparagus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the return of mild temperatures and rain, our wide-ranging Shiitake strains have started fruiting again, as have, for the first time so far, the Wine Cap (King Stropharia) mushrooms Tasha inoculated last year in the mulch beneath our peach trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2016-04-02-reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016/Shiitakes.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Shiitakes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The four excellent strains of Shiitake I purchased from Field and Forest last spring seem to have successfully colonized most of the inoculated logs. I’ve been soaking some of them in the bathtub we bought for use at last year’s pig slaughter to induce them to fruit and stacking them in tee-pee patterns around the trees in our mushroom grotto, the shaded area between the buck pen and the dining area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2016-04-02-reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016/Mushroom Logs.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Mushroom Logs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We built a buck pen for the male goats over the winter. Tasha built the shelter out of reclaimed shipping pallets and some new lumber and even outfitted it with a rainwater collection system and an automatic watering system. We sunk posts and ran fence around the shady area above the duck pond, which hosts some goat forage and provides a comfortable amount of space, but at a distance from the does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2016-04-02-reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016/Buck Pen.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Buck Pen&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We built the separate pen so we can control the does’ pregnancies and milking cycles—we’re up to seven does now—and which goats breed with which. We’re still in the process of finding homes for our two wethers, but Popeye and Moose will remain. Tasha’s getting really good at making cheese.The blue cheeses she made recently with flora Danica smell just like the real deal (we’ll get to taste soon), and she’s been making some amazing fresh cheeses for a while now, having recently added haloumi to the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;img src=/assets/images/2016-04-02-reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016/Does.jpg” title=”Does”&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my own spare time, I’ve been mostly occupying myself with maintenance projects. The semi-transparent pergola which followed us from Maryland and ended up on our terrace here has finally met its end. Last weekend, I spent a day or so rebuilding it with more durable and permanent materials, namely corrugated steel roofing and new pressure-treated framing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2016-04-02-reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016/Outdoor Dining Area.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Outdoor Dining Area&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the pergola and the roof over the pizza oven were starting get a little weathered looking, so I stained them red, which certainly brightened things up a bit. To the table I built last year, I added another few coats of spar varnish, and Tasha weeded and cleaned the patio beneath it, so we’re ready for another season of outdoor living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2016-04-02-reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016/Table.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Table&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides working on the outside dining area, we’ve done a lot of work around the greenhouse and the high pond in front of it. Tasha did some more work on the semi-floating garden in the pond and mulched the paths around it. I put in a couple sets of stairs I cut from railroad ties, at either end of the greenhouse. This not only makes it easier to get to and from the greenhouse, but adds more visual appeal to the area around the pond, where we’ve placed the Adirondack furniture I built at the end of last summer from a load of reclaimed pallet lumber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2016-04-02-reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016/Greenhouse Stairs.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Greenhouse Stairs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is where we aspire to end up after the work’s done, at the end of a string of increasingly gorgeous days, relaxing by the pond and looking up at the stars. Till next time…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2016-04-02-reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016/Adirondack Furniture.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Adirondack Furniture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://the-way-back.com/reluxe-roundups/2016/04/02/reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://the-way-back.com/reluxe-roundups/2016/04/02/reluxe-mega-roundup-april-3-2016.html</guid>
        
        <category>homesteading</category>
        
        <category>turkeys</category>
        
        <category>goats</category>
        
        <category>mushrooms</category>
        
        
        <category>reluxe-roundups</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
